<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 
 <title>Schur's Lemming</title>
 <link href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href=""/>
 <updated>2019-07-16T08:37:28+00:00</updated>
 <id></id>
 <author>
   <name>Ninnat Dangniam</name>
   <email>truecrimson@gmail.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>May-July 2019 Archive</title>
   <link href="/may-2019-log.html"/>
   <updated>2019-07-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>h/may-2019-log</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is an archive of what I found useful, interesting, or simply enjoyable from May, June and some of July 2019. My research reading in the past couple of months has been a bit nebulous and hard to summarize so I want to leave that out for now .&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;toc&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;!-- # Research

Research is a bit nebulous these months, with so much that I want to talk about but so little that I can comfortably do.

- [Efficient verification of bosonic quantum channels via benchmarking](https://arxiv.org/abs/1904.10682), Wu and Sanders 1904.10682
    - [Reliable quantum certification of photonic state preparations](https://arxiv.org/abs/1407.4817), Aolita, Gogolin, Kliesch and Eisert 2015
        - [Graphical calculus for Gaussian pure states](https://arxiv.org/abs/1007.0725), Menicucci, Flammia and van Loock 2011
    - [Fidelity witnesses for fermionic quantum simulations](http://arxiv.org/abs/1703.03152), Gluza , Kliesch, Eisert and Aolita 2018
    - [Certifying quantumness: Benchmarks for the optimal processing of generalized coherent and squeezed states](http://arxiv.org/abs/1407.4133), Yang, Chiribella and Adesso 2015
- [Phase space simulation method for quantum computation with magic states on qubits](https://scirate.com/arxiv/1905.05374), Raussendorf et al. 1905.05374 [[Scirate discussion](https://scirate.com/arxiv/1905.05374#1342)]   
- [All fermionic non-Gaussian states are magic states for matchgate computations](https://scirate.com/arxiv/1905.08584), Hebenstreit et al. 1905.08584 --&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;media&quot;&gt;Media&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bangkokpost.com/lifestyle/social-and-lifestyle/314880/a-lifelong-love-of-learning&quot;&gt;Prasert Na Nagara&lt;/a&gt; (ประเสริฐ ณ นคร) 1919 - 2019&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mitchell Feigenbaum, a pioneer of chaos theory &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rockefeller.edu/news/26289-mitchell-feigenbaum-physicist-pioneered-chaos-theory-died/&quot;&gt;passed away&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-qgreAUpPwM&quot;&gt;Drawing with Fourier series and epicycles&lt;/a&gt;, 3Blue1Brown&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.insidehighered.com/news/2019/05/03/icelands-universities-worry-about-small-numbers-male-students-they-attract&quot;&gt;Males are underrepresented in Iceland higher education&lt;/a&gt; because fishing career is more attractive. “in 2017 Icelandic men still earned 15.5 percent more per hour than women.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://praxis.fortelabs.co/how-emotions-are-made/&quot;&gt;How Emotions Are Made: The Theory of Constructed Emotion&lt;/a&gt;, Tiago Forte&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you experience an emotion without knowing the precise cause, you are more likely to treat that emotion as information about the &lt;em&gt;world&lt;/em&gt;, rather than your &lt;em&gt;experience&lt;/em&gt; of the world. This is known as &lt;em&gt;affective realism&lt;/em&gt;. Affective realism causes us to experience supposed “facts” about the world that are in fact created by our feelings. It can leave us trapped in an emotional world of our own making, without realizing that we are the ones who imprisoned ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you can learn to distinguish more precise meanings for “Feeling great” (happy, content, thrilled, relaxed, joyful, hopeful, inspired, prideful, adoring, grateful, blissful . . .) or “Feeling crappy” (angry, aggravated, alarmed, spiteful, grumpy, remorseful, gloomy, mortified, uneasy, dread-ridden, resentful, afraid, envious, woeful, melancholy . . .), your brain will have many more options for predicting, categorizing, and perceiving emotions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kevin Simler has an interactive blog post on &lt;a href=&quot;https://meltingasphalt.com/interactive/going-critical/&quot;&gt;network criticality&lt;/a&gt; that nicely illustrates concepts like herd immunity and transmission of knowledge. One point that is obvious once heard but I’ve never internalized before:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;there are ideas and cultural practices that can take root and spread in a city that simply can’t spread out in the countryside. (Mathematically can’t.) These are the very same ideas and the very same kinds of people. It’s not that rural folks are e.g. “small-minded”; when exposed to one of these ideas, they’re exactly as likely to adopt it as someone in the city. Rather, it’s that the idea itself can’t go viral in the countryside because there aren’t as many connections along which it can spread.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://hbr.org/2019/03/the-feedback-fallacy&quot;&gt;The feedback fallacy&lt;/a&gt;, HBR&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Excellence is also not the opposite of failure. […] Study disease and you will learn a lot about disease and precious little about health. Eradicating depression will get you no closer to joy. Divorce is mute on the topic of happy marriage. Exit interviews with employees who leave tell you nothing about why others stay. If you study failure, you’ll learn a lot about failure but nothing about how to achieve excellence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A candidate gene for depression is another house of cards. [&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/science/archive/2019/05/waste-1000-studies/589684/&quot;&gt;Atlantic&lt;/a&gt;] [&lt;a href=&quot;https://slatestarcodex.com/2019/05/07/5-httlpr-a-pointed-review/&quot;&gt;SSC&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;First time the world has &lt;a href=&quot;https://ourworldindata.org/population-aged-65-outnumber-children&quot;&gt;more people over 64 than children younger than 5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ft.com/content/cf19b956-60a2-11e9-b285-3acd5d43599e&quot;&gt;Who is using your face?&lt;/a&gt;, FT [&lt;a href=&quot;https://old.reddit.com/r/EmergingRisks/comments/bewxkp/whos_using_your_face_the_ugly_truth_about_facial/&quot;&gt;without paywall&lt;/a&gt;] [&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2019/07/13/technology/databases-faces-facial-recognition-technology.html&quot;&gt;NYTimes&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the low-trust society, the Chinese welcome &lt;a href=&quot;https://slate.com/technology/2019/05/china-mobile-5g-facial-recognition-ad.html&quot;&gt;facial recognition technology&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mpg.de/13566273/periodic-system-elements&quot;&gt;The periodic system as ordered hypergraphs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lanthanum hydride, a compound rich in hydrogen exhibits &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-019-01583-y&quot;&gt;superconductivity at 250 K&lt;/a&gt; under more than a million times Earth’s atmospheric pressure. In general, the lower the atomic mass, the higher the critical temperature.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://english.stackexchange.com/questions/448865/is-the-etymology-of-salary-a-myth&quot;&gt;myth of the etymology of salary&lt;/a&gt; from salarium, “salt money”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://castel.dev/post/lecture-notes-1/&quot;&gt;How I’m able to take notes in mathematics lectures using LaTeX and Vim&lt;/a&gt;, Gilles Castel&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/notable/notable&quot;&gt;Notable&lt;/a&gt;, a markdown-based, Wikipedia-style note-taking app, currently with &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/notable/notable/issues&quot;&gt;numerous bugs&lt;/a&gt; and inconveniences (e.g. can’t define global LaTeX macros, single-letter LaTeX codes don’t render)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://stackoverflow.com/a/47527140&quot;&gt;Collaboratory&lt;/a&gt; let you share Jupyter notebooks with collaborators.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.polygon.com/2019/6/19/18683634/neon-genesis-evangelion-hideaki-anno-depression-shinji-anime-characters-movies&quot;&gt;Neverending Evangelion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a statement of intent titled “What Were We Trying To Make Here,” drafted in July 1995 during production of this new series, Anno wrote: “I tried to include everything of myself in Neon Genesis Evangelion — myself, a broken man who could do nothing for four years. A man who ran away for four years, one who was simply not dead. Then one thought. ‘You can’t run away,’ came to me, and I restarted this production. It is a production where my only thought was to burn my feelings into film.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In episode 16, about halfway through production of the series, creatively blocked and unable to go further writing the story for the character of the ambiguous Rei, Anno asked a friend for a suggestion on some reading about mental illness in an attempt to better understand her. The book he picked up startled him. What he found within was a diagnosis of his own problems in life. It was revelatory. Anno had been struggling with depression all these years and hadn’t had the language or understanding for it, or even accepted that it could be a clinical diagnosis. Evangelion changed after Anno recognized his own life’s struggle. The show became more tragic, and more apocalyptic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In what remains of a few fan-translated fragments of a Japanese interview conducted by manga author Nariko Enomoto, finishing the series while recognizing his own depression left Anno in a state of deep existential crisis. He reportedly contemplated suicide. Hayao Miyazaki consoled him, a memory that to this day moves Anno to tears. He has stressed over the years how much of himself he put into Evangelion, and how it left him utterly empty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anno later declared in the Japanese magazine NewType that “Evangelion is like a puzzle, you know. Any person can see it and give his/her own answer. In other words, we’re offering viewers to think by themselves, so that each person can imagine his/her own world. We will never offer the answers, even in the theatrical version. As for many Evangelion viewers, they may expect us to provide the ‘all-about Eva’ manuals, but there is no such thing. Don’t expect to get answers by someone. Don’t expect to be catered to all the time. We all have to find our own answers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/QiaochuYuan/status/1132020145851736066&quot;&gt;Why do stories need ending?&lt;/a&gt;, Qiaochu Yuan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SSC book reviews:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://slatestarcodex.com/2019/06/04/book-review-the-secret-of-our-success/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Secret of Our Success&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (Highly recommended, too long to summarize here)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://slatestarcodex.com/2018/11/28/book-review-the-mind-illuminated/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Mind Illuminated&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/hnLutdvjC8kPScPAj/integrating-disagreeing-subagents&quot;&gt;Integrating disagreeing subagents&lt;/a&gt;, Kaj Sotala&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gwern.net/The-Narrowing-Circle&quot;&gt;The Narrowing Circle&lt;/a&gt;, Gwern (Our experience strongly points toward the “expanding circle” thesis being true, that human ethics expand over time to include more people, more organisms, more things. But is that really the case?)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Japanese &lt;a href=&quot;https://mymodernmet.com/japanese-rice-paddy-art&quot;&gt;rice paddy art&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sit back, relax, and enjoy watching Protozoans while listening to Hank Green&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;
https://www.youtube.com/embed/PZoaKzEXzi8?controls=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;environmenteconomicspolicies&quot;&gt;Environment/economics/policies&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are more &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Energy_accidents#Fatalities&quot;&gt;deaths per petawatt hour&lt;/a&gt; from rooftop solar panel installation than those from nuclear power.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Greenland ice melt has become extreme in the past decade, &lt;a href=&quot;https://edition.cnn.com/2019/06/14/us/greenland-sudden-ice-melt-wxc/index.html&quot;&gt;losing two gigaton of ice on one day this year&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://nsidc.org/greenland-today/greenland-surface-melt-extent-interactive-chart/&quot;&gt;Plots&lt;/a&gt; from Greenland’s National Snow and Ice Center.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;White House &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/climate-environment/2019/06/08/white-house-blocked-intelligence-aides-written-testimony-saying-human-caused-climate-change-could-be-possibly-catastrophic/?utm_term=.36fad422e920&quot;&gt;barred an intelligence agency&lt;/a&gt; from a written submission that warns againsts the risk of climate change. One of the critics is an atomic physicist &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/2019/03/01/698073442/heres-the-white-houses-top-climate-change-skeptic&quot;&gt;William Happer&lt;/a&gt; who has long been arguing for a benefit of increasing CO2.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/Economics/comments/5g6ese/the_simple_analytics_of_an_nit_ubi_and_eitc/&quot;&gt;The simple analytics of UBI, NIT, and EITC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SSC on &lt;a href=&quot;https://slatestarcodex.com/2019/06/10/book-review-the-prices-are-too-dmn-high/&quot;&gt;Baumol’s cost disease&lt;/a&gt; and a &lt;a href=&quot;https://slatestarcodex.com/2019/06/17/followup-on-the-baumol-effect-thanks-o-baumol/&quot;&gt;follow-up&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A standard example of the power of default opt-in: organ donation is &lt;a href=&quot;https://jasoncollins.blog/2015/02/11/charts-that-dont-seem-quite-right-organ-donation-edition/&quot;&gt;misleading&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nybooks.com/articles/2019/05/09/kidnapping-efficient-business/&quot;&gt;Kidnapping: A Very Efficient Business&lt;/a&gt;, NY Review of Books [&lt;a href=&quot;https://sundiatapost.com/2019/04/28/world-of-kidnapping-a-very-efficient-business/&quot;&gt;Without paywall&lt;/a&gt;] [&lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=19712238&quot;&gt;ycombinator&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;quantummachine-learning&quot;&gt;Quantum/machine learning&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://openai.com/blog/musenet&quot;&gt;MuseNet&lt;/a&gt;, a neural network that learns musical styles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://nostalgebraist.tumblr.com/post/185326092369/the-transformer-explained&quot;&gt;Transformer architecture explained&lt;/a&gt; (GPT-2, BERT, AlphaStar)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=p1b5aiTrGzY&quot;&gt;Few-Shot Adversarial Learning of Realistic Neural Talking Head Models&lt;/a&gt; (Go to the end of the video to see Marilyn Monroe, Einstein, and Mona Lisa talking.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ewin Tang’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://ewintang.com/blog/2019/01/28/an-overview-of-quantum-inspired-sampling/&quot;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; on her quantum-inspired machine learning algorithms. &lt;em&gt;Related:&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1905.10415&quot;&gt;Quantum-inspired algorithms in practice&lt;/a&gt;, Arrazola, Delgado, Bardhan and Lloyd 1905.10415&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.quantamagazine.org/does-nevens-law-describe-quantum-computings-rise-20190618/&quot;&gt;Neven’s Law&lt;/a&gt;: the number of qubits increase doubly exponentially with time. Thus, so they say, quantum supremacy is right around the corner. Compare this to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nap.edu/catalog/25196/quantum-computing-progress-and-prospects&quot;&gt;the 2019 consensus report&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although many people think that there will be a Moore’s law-type scaling for the number of qubits in a system, it is important to remember that Moore’s law resulted from a virtuous cycle, where improved technology generated exponentially increasing revenue, enabling reinvestment in research and development (R&amp;amp;D) and attracting new talent and industries to help innovate and scale the technology to the next level. As with silicon technology, a Moore’s law-type of sustained exponential growth for qubits requires an exponentially growing investment, sustaining this investment will likely require a similar virtuous cycle for quantum computers […]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An honest and informative &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cd1MSiH8vGA&quot;&gt;interview about NISQ computers&lt;/a&gt;, Software Engineering Institute, Carnegie Mellon [&lt;a href=&quot;https://resources.sei.cmu.edu/asset_files/Video/2019_500_100_546391.pdf&quot;&gt;transcript&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.quantamagazine.org/how-to-turn-a-quantum-computer-into-the-ultimate-randomness-generator-20190619/&quot;&gt;Certified random numbers&lt;/a&gt; from NISQ machines&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sabine Hossenfelder: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GKnfVA1v5ow&quot;&gt;“[NISQ] is really a term invented to make investors believe that quantum computing will have practical applications in the next decade or so.”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scott Aaronson on Neven’s law and Sabine: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4207&quot;&gt;Quantum of Solace&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4220&quot;&gt;Quantum Sabinacy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chris Monroe: &lt;a href=&quot;https://venturebeat.com/2019/04/21/quantum-computing-is-a-marathon-not-a-sprint/&quot;&gt;Quantum computing is a marathon not a sprint&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pbs.org/wgbh/nova/article/what-makes-great-qubit-diamonds-and-ions-could-hold-answer&quot;&gt;Diamond- and ion-based qubits&lt;/a&gt;, PBS Nova&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-019-00647-3&quot;&gt;Continuous-variable information processing&lt;/a&gt; with GKP code and exponential SWAP, Nature News and Views&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chemistry is &lt;a href=&quot;https://cen.acs.org/articles/95/i43/Chemistry-quantum-computings-killer-app.html&quot;&gt;quantum computing’s killer app&lt;/a&gt;, American Chemistry Society&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Boston Consulting Group &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bcg.com/publications/2019/quantum-computers-create-value-when.aspx&quot;&gt;analyzes the future value created by quantum computers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chris Granade and Sarah Kaiser are writing a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.manning.com/books/learn-quantum-computing-with-python-and-q-sharp&quot;&gt;book&lt;/a&gt; on quantum programming with Python and Q#&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.quantamagazine.org/computer-scientists-expand-the-frontier-of-verifiable-knowledge-20190523/&quot;&gt;NEEXP is contained in quantum MIP&lt;/a&gt;, Quanta [&lt;a href=&quot;https://mycqstate.wordpress.com/2019/04/14/randomness-and-interaction-entanglement-ups-the-game/&quot;&gt;Thomas Vidick&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;David Deutsch &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theringer.com/movies/2019/5/3/18527776/marvel-avengers-endgame-time-travel-david-deutsch-proposition-scott-aaronson&quot;&gt;has no idea&lt;/a&gt; what “Deutsch’s proposition” in &lt;em&gt;Avengers: Endgame&lt;/em&gt; means.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hC3ckLqsL5M&quot;&gt;interview&lt;/a&gt; with Tim Maudlin on quantum interpretations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Minute Physics explains &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lvTqbM5Dq4Q&quot;&gt;Shor’s algorithm&lt;/a&gt;, with a follow-up &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FRZQ-efABeQ&quot;&gt;example&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://blogs.scientificamerican.com/cross-check/quantum-computing-for-english-majors/&quot;&gt;“Ask Peter Shor Anything”&lt;/a&gt; (Math proofs, the infamous &lt;a href=&quot;https://spectrum.ieee.org/computing/hardware/the-case-against-quantum-computing&quot;&gt;Dyakonov’s article&lt;/a&gt;, arguments from beauty in physics, anti-science movements)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;musics&quot;&gt;Musics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;RichaadEB
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zG325qCKH9o&quot;&gt;Pure Furies ~ Whereabouts of the Heart&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ugqjcXjpCts&quot;&gt;Night of Nights&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://vgmdb.net/album/88456&quot;&gt;Bloodstained: Ritual of the Night&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KPtF0yAQ1KY&quot;&gt;Voyage of Promise&lt;/a&gt; [&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kc1ObxtJSJ4&quot;&gt;Gabocarina96&lt;/a&gt;] / &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jBtcs3VE_Ws&quot;&gt;Bibliotheca Ex Machina&lt;/a&gt;, Michiru Yamane&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vg8damWdjR0&quot;&gt;Gears of Fortune&lt;/a&gt; [&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zHgbvnlo-2k&quot;&gt;RichaadEB&lt;/a&gt;], Ryusuke Fujioka&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dIH1nOPvrQ0&quot;&gt;Veil&lt;/a&gt;, Keina Suda {Enen no Shouboutai} [ED]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;books&quot;&gt;Books&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Non-fiction&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Blueprint: How DNA Makes Us Who We Are&lt;/em&gt;, Plomin 2018
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gwern.net/docs/genetics/2016-plomin.pdf&quot;&gt;Top 10 Replicated Findings From Behavioral Genetics&lt;/a&gt;, Plomin, DeFries, Knopik and Neiderhiser 2016&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/mp2014105&quot;&gt;Genetics and intelligence differences: five special findings&lt;/a&gt;, Plomin and Deary 2014&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recommended; the first part of the book covers robust classic findings from decades of adoption and twin studies, &lt;!--(such as Colorado Adoption project (n = 250 + 250 controls) and Twin Early Development Study (n = 16000))--&gt; namely the counterintuitive &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.psychologytoday.com/gb/blog/the-scientific-fundamentalist/200809/the-50-0-50-rule-why-parenting-has-virtually-no-effect&quot;&gt;50-0-50 rule&lt;/a&gt;: parenting and schooling have virtually no effect on childrens, while the rest of the contribution comes equally from genetics and “unshared environment” which can be &lt;a href=&quot;https://slatestarcodex.com/2016/03/16/non-shared-environment-doesnt-just-mean-schools-and-peers/&quot;&gt;anything including measurement errors&lt;/a&gt;. Very roughly speaking, any phenotype &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(p\)&lt;/span&gt; has two contributions: genetic &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(g\)&lt;/span&gt; and environmental &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(e\)&lt;/span&gt;. So the variance is &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\[ \Var(p) = \Var(g) + \Var(e) + 2\Cov(g,e) \]&lt;/span&gt; Heritability (“in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heritability#Definition&quot;&gt;broad sense&lt;/a&gt;”) is defined to be &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\Var(g)/\Var(p)\)&lt;/span&gt;. Once controlled for the “nature of nurture”, &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\Cov(g,e) = 0\)&lt;/span&gt;, the effect of nurture often disappears.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Divorce&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first genetic study of divorce caused a stir. In a study of 1,500 pairs of adult twins, concordance for divorce was much greater for identical than for fraternal twins (55 per cent versus 16 per cent) […] It has long been known that the offspring of divorced parents are more likely to get divorced themselves. Possible environmental explanations leap to mind, for example, living through their parents’ divorce causes children to have relationship problems, or because they do not have good models for a stable relationship. However, a recent adoption study in Sweden showed that the link between divorce in parents and divorce in their children is forged genetically, not environmentally. For a sample of 20,000 adopted individuals, the likelihood of divorce was greater if their biological mother, who did not rear the individual, had later in life become divorced than if the adoptive parents who reared them had become divorced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The heritability of divorce is about 40 per cent across studies. This is a long way from 100 per cent, meaning that non-genetic factors are also important. However, the major systematic factor affecting divorce is genetics. In contrast, no environmental predictors of divorce have been identified in research after controlling for genetics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watching TV&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Children’s television viewing is a quintessential measure of the environment, which, by the 1980s, had been used in more than 2,000 studies exploring its effect on children’s development. None of these studies questioned the assumption that how much television children watched was a measure of the environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;most parents back then put no restrictions on the amount of time their children watched television. How much children watched television was up to the children, which leaves the door open for genetic differences between children to shape how much television they watch. […] Non-adoptive parents and their children were significantly more similar (0.30) in how much television they watched than were adoptive parents and their adopted children (0.15). […] The most astonishing result was that birth mothers’ television viewing correlated significantly (0.15) with their adopted-away children’s television viewing, even though these birth mothers had not seen their adopted-away children after the first week of life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;we can turn the television on or off as we please, but turning it off or leaving it on pleases individuals differently, in part due to genetic factors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other psychological experiences&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since then, more than 150 papers have looked at environmental measures in genetically sensitive studies. They consistently find substantial genetic influence and the average heritability is still about 25 per cent. What’s new is that these studies have greatly extended the list of environmental measures that show genetic influence. For example, evidence for genetic influence has been found for home environments such as chaotic family environments, for classroom environments such as supportive teachers, peer characteristics such as being bullied, neighbourhood safety, being exposed to drugs, work environments and the quality of one’s marriage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you start thinking about how much DNA matters, it is difficult to point to any psychological experiences completely devoid of possible genetic influence. For example, accidents are not always accidental. Some children have more accidents than others; the number of children’s scrapes and bruises shows genetic influence. For adults, automobile accidents are not always accidental either, of course. Automobile crashes are often caused by reckless driving – driving too fast, taking chances or driving under the influence of alcohol and other drugs. Sometimes accidents do just happen, but genetic differences in personality can increase the likelihood of accidents happening. […] The only events free from genetic influence are those over which we have little control, such as the death or illness of relatives and friends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The author understandably spends a lot of time discussing how the result could be true and how &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to misinterpret. Crucially, the measure is statistical and hence accurate on the population level, not the individual level. The result is conditioned on “normal” experience e.g. no neglect, torture etc. More generally, equality of opportunity means more pronounced genetic effects because privilege means less.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Parenting&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;parenting correlates with children’s outcomes for three reasons considered earlier. One reason is that parents and their children are 50 per cent similar genetically. Put crudely, nice parents have nice children because they are all nice genetically. Another reason is that parenting is often a response to, rather than a cause of, children’s genetic propensities. It is awkward to be an affectionate parent to a child who is not a cuddler. Finally, children make their own environments, regardless of their parents. That is, they select, modify and create environments correlated with their genetic propensities. Children who want to do something like play sports or a musical instrument will badger their parents to make it happen. […]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;genetic research describes &lt;em&gt;what is&lt;/em&gt;, not &lt;em&gt;what could be&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second half of the book goes into the genetic basis of psychological behaviors and how, with increasingly low cost of genome sequencing, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Genome-wide_association_study&quot;&gt;GWAS&lt;/a&gt; has become a powerful tool to solve the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Missing_heritability_problem&quot;&gt;missing heritability problem&lt;/a&gt;: if behaviors are 50% genetic, where are the genes responsible for them? &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polygenic_score&quot;&gt;Polygenic scores&lt;/a&gt; can now predict 7% of variance of the susceptibility for Schizophrenia, 4% for major depressive disorder, 10% for bipolar disorder, 5% of Alzeimer’s disease &lt;a href=&quot;#fn1&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot; id=&quot;fnref1&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and &amp;gt;10% for years of education (already &amp;gt;15% &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/kph3k/status/1009875245900156928&quot;&gt;last year&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fiction&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Old Man and the Sea&lt;/em&gt;, Hemmingway 1952&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://myanimelist.net/manga/98270/Fire_Punch&quot;&gt;Fire Punch&lt;/a&gt; Vol. 1-8 (completed) and &lt;a href=&quot;https://myanimelist.net/manga/116778/Chainsaw_Man&quot;&gt;Chainsaw Man&lt;/a&gt;, Fujimoto Tatsuki&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;anime&quot;&gt;Anime&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kizumonogatari: &lt;a href=&quot;https://myanimelist.net/anime/9260/Kizumonogatari_I__Tekketsu-hen&quot;&gt;Tekketsu-hen&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://myanimelist.net/anime/31757/Kizumonogatari_II__Nekketsu-hen&quot;&gt;Nekketsu-hen&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://myanimelist.net/anime/31758/Kizumonogatari_III__Reiketsu-hen&quot;&gt;Reiketsu-hen&lt;/a&gt;, Shaft {Nisio Isin} [Light novel] 2016, 2017 &lt;em&gt;(Rewatch)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://myanimelist.net/anime/10357/Jinrui_wa_Suitai_Shimashita&quot;&gt;Jinrui wa Suitai Shimashita&lt;/a&gt; (12 Episodes), AIC A.S.T.A. {Tanaka Romeo} [Light novel] 2012 Notable episode: 8 (My headcanon is that the fairies are Robin Hanson’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://ageofem.com/&quot;&gt;EMs&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://myanimelist.net/anime/35557/Houseki_no_Kuni&quot;&gt;Houseki no Kuni&lt;/a&gt; (12 Episodes), Orange {Ichikawa Haruko} [Manga] 2017 (Better than the manga)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://myanimelist.net/anime/37999/Kaguya-sama_wa_Kokurasetai__Tensai-tachi_no_Renai_Zunousen&quot;&gt;Kaguya-sama wa Kokurasetai&lt;/a&gt; (12 Episodes), A-1 Pictures {Akasaka Aka} [Manga] 2019&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;video-games&quot;&gt;Video games&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://vgmdb.net/album/88456&quot;&gt;Bloodstained: Ritual of the Night&lt;/a&gt; (ROTN), a spiritual successor of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Castlevania:_Symphony_of_the_Night&quot;&gt;one of the best games of all time&lt;/a&gt; (SOTN)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pros:&lt;/em&gt; What sold me was the musics by Michiru Yamane, among others. The game itself is fun with plenty of replay values and not as easy as SOTN e.g. the first boss in hard mode is Nintendo hard. There are varieties of movement options and intentional glitches for speedrunning and sequence-breaking. &lt;em&gt;Cons:&lt;/em&gt; The graphic looks toy-ish and “cheap”. I wish they take advantage of different camera angles more. &lt;em&gt;Not really a con but a warning to keyboard users:&lt;/em&gt; &lt;code&gt;Aim&lt;/code&gt; doesn’t seem to work if assigned to a keyboard button. A touchpad button is fine but clunky and downright impractical mid-combat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn1&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;In these cases, polygenic scores are more powerful predictors than traditional ones such as the psychollogical disorders in parents. Most traits are highly &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polygene&quot;&gt;polygenic&lt;/a&gt;, with an exception of Alzheimer’s disease which is mostly due to a single gene call [&lt;em&gt;APOE&lt;/em&gt;](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apolipoprotein_E#Alzheimer’s_disease).&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>March-April 2019 Archive</title>
   <link href="/mar-apr-2019-log.html"/>
   <updated>2019-05-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>h/mar-apr-2019-log</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is an archive of what I found useful, interesting, or simply enjoyable from March and April 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;toc&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;research&quot;&gt;Research&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;stabilizer-quantum-mechanics&quot;&gt;Stabilizer quantum mechanics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1703.00111&quot;&gt;Unbiased Simulation of Near-Clifford Quantum Circuits&lt;/a&gt;, Bennink et al. 2017&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1901.09070&quot;&gt;Simulation of Qubit Quantum Circuits via Pauli Propagation&lt;/a&gt;, Rall, Liang, Cook and Kretschmer 1901.09070&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/abs/1902.11257&quot;&gt;Efficient classical simulation of Clifford circuits with nonstabilizer input states&lt;/a&gt;, Bu and Koh 1902.11257&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\mathcal{C}_3\)&lt;/span&gt; be a circuit composed of gates from the third level of &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/quant-ph/9908010&quot;&gt;Clifford hierarchy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Theorem 1.&lt;/strong&gt; The output probabilities of a circuit &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\mathcal{C}_3\)&lt;/span&gt; on &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(n+m\)&lt;/span&gt; qubits with input state &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\ketbra{0}{0}^{\otimes n} \otimes^m_{j=1} \rho_j\)&lt;/span&gt; and computational basis measurement can be approximated up to &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(l_1\)&lt;/span&gt; norm &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\delta\)&lt;/span&gt; in &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\[(n+m)^{\mathcal{O}(1)} m^{\mathcal{O}\left[ \log \left( \sqrt{\alpha} /\delta \right)/\lambda \right]}.\]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\lambda\)&lt;/span&gt; measures the mixedness of the most pure &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\rho_j\)&lt;/span&gt;, namely the &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\lambda = \epsilon\)&lt;/span&gt; for every qubit state of the form &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\((1-\epsilon)\ketbra{\psi}{\psi} + \epsilon\id/2\)&lt;/span&gt;. The &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(1-2/\alpha\)&lt;/span&gt; comes from using the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Markov%27s_inequality&quot;&gt;Markov inequality&lt;/a&gt; on the average of the &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(l_1\)&lt;/span&gt; norm of the Fourier coefficients of the output probabilities over the uniform distribution of Cliffords (a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quantum_t-design#Unitary_t-Designs&quot;&gt;unitary 2-design&lt;/a&gt;). Since qudit (&lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(d \ge 3\)&lt;/span&gt;) Cliffords also form a 2-design, the latter technique should generalize. (The set of qubit Cliffords is not just a 2-design but also a &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1510.02619&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;-&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1510.02769&quot;&gt;design&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When every input state is pure, the exponent blows up. For that, we have&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Theorem 2&lt;/strong&gt; The output probabilities of a circuit &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\mathcal{C}_3\)&lt;/span&gt; on &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(n+m\)&lt;/span&gt; qubits with input state &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\ket{0}^{\otimes n} \otimes^m_{j=1} \ket{\psi_j}\)&lt;/span&gt; and computational basis measurement on &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(k\)&lt;/span&gt; qubits, the number of of unmeasured qubits being greater than the log of the &lt;em&gt;Pauli rank&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\[ n+m-k \ge \sum^m_{j=1} \log \left( \frac{\chi(\psi_j)}{2} \right), \]&lt;/span&gt; can be approximated up to &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(l_1\)&lt;/span&gt; norm &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\delta\)&lt;/span&gt; in &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\[ (n+m)^{\mathcal{O}(1)} m^{\mathcal{O}\left[ \log \left( \sqrt{\alpha} /\delta \right)/\mu \right]}, \]&lt;/span&gt; where now &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\[ \mu(\psi) := 2(1-\max_{\phi \in \mathrm{stab}} |\av{\phi|\psi}|^2). \]&lt;/span&gt; The fidelity to the closest stabilizer state is the &lt;em&gt;stabilizer rank&lt;/em&gt;. Curiously, the more “stabilizer-ness” the &lt;em&gt;worse&lt;/em&gt; the runtime!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The method is inspired by &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1810.03176&quot;&gt;“Efficient classical simulation of noisy quantum computation”&lt;/a&gt; by Gao and Duan, and much like that paper, Bu and Koh’s paper is about &lt;em&gt;average-case&lt;/em&gt; difficulty. Notably Gao and Duan’s paper gives a classical simulation of a random quantum circuit with constant noise, seemingly contradicting the threshold theorem, but a fault-tolerant circuit is hardly a random circuit.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Having talked to Kaifeng Bu, I should read his &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1812.00224&quot;&gt;“Classical simulation of quantum circuits by half Gauss sums”&lt;/a&gt;. Interestingly, the paper also has something to say about the “Holant function”, &lt;a href=&quot;http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/download?doi=10.1.1.634.7031&amp;amp;rep=rep1&amp;amp;type=pdf&quot;&gt;related to perfect matchings on weighted graphs&lt;/a&gt; (“matchgate tensors”).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;representation-theory&quot;&gt;Representation theory&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://people.maths.ox.ac.uk/~sanders/acha/notes.pdf&quot;&gt;Applications of commutative harmonic analysis&lt;/a&gt;, Sanders (Convolutions in analysis, random walks, combinatorics, and number theory)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://web.science.mq.edu.au/~street/CT90Como.pdf&quot;&gt;An introduction to Tannaka duality and quantum groups&lt;/a&gt;, Joyal and Street&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Algebraic geometry&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Linear Algebraic Groups&lt;/em&gt;, Humphreys 1998&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;John Baez on &lt;a href=&quot;https://johncarlosbaez.wordpress.com/2018/12/01/geometric-quantization-part-1/&quot;&gt;Geometric quantization&lt;/a&gt; [&lt;a href=&quot;http://nautil.us/issue/69/patterns/the-math-that-takes-newton-into-the-quantum-world&quot;&gt;Nautilus&lt;/a&gt; article on how algebraic geometry (“Hartshorne”), or rather algebraic topology finally clicked for him]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to some school of thought, quantization is a process of taking a symplectic manifold &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(M\)&lt;/span&gt; and turn it into a complex Hilbert space (and smooth functions–classical observables–to linear operators). But that is really just a “&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Geometric_quantization#Prequantization&quot;&gt;prequantization&lt;/a&gt;”. Baez &lt;a href=&quot;https://johncarlosbaez.wordpress.com/2018/12/26/geometric-quantization-part-2/&quot;&gt;points out&lt;/a&gt;. We need much more than that; we need a line bundle &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(L\)&lt;/span&gt; over &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(M\)&lt;/span&gt; and various structures (even if &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(M\)&lt;/span&gt; is already Kähler) that make &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(L\)&lt;/span&gt; compatible with the symplectic, complex, and Riemannian structure on &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(M\)&lt;/span&gt;. (&lt;a href=&quot;https://johncarlosbaez.wordpress.com/2018/12/30/geometric-quantization-part-5/&quot;&gt;This&lt;/a&gt; shows you how it works for 2-spheres.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The world is quantum so perhaps it makes little sense to expect that just the symplectic structure can take us all the way to the complex Hilbert space. Instead, Baez &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Partially_ordered_set&quot;&gt;proposing&lt;/a&gt;, let us start with a complex projective variety &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\C P^n \subset \C^{n+1}\)&lt;/span&gt;, then take the smallest subspace in &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(V \subset \C^{n+1}\)&lt;/span&gt; whose &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Projectivization&quot;&gt;projectivized&lt;/a&gt; space &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\mathbb{P}V\)&lt;/span&gt; contains &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(M\)&lt;/span&gt; to be its quantization &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(Q(M) = V\)&lt;/span&gt;. Projectivization then gives back &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(P(V) = M\)&lt;/span&gt;. In this way, we have &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Partially_ordered_set&quot;&gt;poset&lt;/a&gt; categories &lt;code&gt;Class&lt;/code&gt; of classical state spaces and &lt;code&gt;Quant&lt;/code&gt; of quantum state spaces and a pair of adjoint functors between them. You can make them &lt;a href=&quot;https://johncarlosbaez.wordpress.com/2018/12/28/geometric-quantization-part-4/&quot;&gt;monoidal&lt;/a&gt; (essentially having the tensor product structure—Segre embedding for varieties) and &lt;a href=&quot;https://johncarlosbaez.wordpress.com/2019/01/08/geometric-quantization-part-7/&quot;&gt;clone&lt;/a&gt; the system with symmetrized product (Veronese embedding for varieties). The latter is actually how you take a classical limit of generalized coherent states (equivalently, &lt;a href=&quot;https://johncarlosbaez.wordpress.com/2019/01/21/geometric-quantization-part-8/&quot;&gt;scaling up the symplectic structure&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(HV\)&lt;/span&gt;-varieties&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On a class of quasihomogeneous affine varieties, Popov and Vinberg 1972 [&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.researchgate.net/publication/250887431_On_a_class_of_quasihomogeneous_affine_varieties&quot;&gt;English translation: Math USSR Izvestija 6 743-58&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Symmetry, Representations, and Invariants&lt;/em&gt;, Goodman and Wallach 2009 (Exercise 12.2.5.2)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“&lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(HV\)&lt;/span&gt;-varieties of small codimensions” in &lt;em&gt;Tangents and Secants of Algebraic Varieties&lt;/em&gt;, Zak 1993&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On Spherical Double Cones, Littelmann 1994&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Complexity and rank of actions in invariant theory, Panyushev 1999&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Homogeneous Spaces and Equivalent Embeddings&lt;/em&gt;, Timashev 2011&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;linear-programming&quot;&gt;Linear programming&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathoverflow.net/a/145079/54448&quot;&gt;Why are optimization problems called “programs”?&lt;/a&gt;, MO&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The military refer to their various plans or proposed schedules of training, logistical supply and deployment of combat units as a program. When I first analyzed the Air Force planning problem and saw that it could be formulated as a system of linear inequalities, I called my paper Programming in a Linear Structure. Note that the term ‘program’ was used for linear programs long before it was used as the set of instructions used by a computer. In the early days, these instructions were called codes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1017/S0962492900002646&quot;&gt;Eigenvalue optimization [paywalled]&lt;/a&gt;, Lewis and Overton 1996 &lt;!-- [Minimum $l_{\infty}$ Norm Solutions To Finite Dimensional Algebraic Underdetermined Linear Systems](http://wiredspace.wits.ac.za/bitstream/handle/10539/16858/20140910_Infinity%2020Norm%20Minimization_MSc%20Thesis_EarleAC.pdf?sequence=1), Adam Christopher Earle, University of Witwatersrand thesis 2014 --&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Minimizing the largest eigenvalue (minimizing the &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(l_{\infty}\)&lt;/span&gt;-norm) &lt;a href=&quot;https://math.stackexchange.com/questions/2589887/how-can-the-infinity-norm-minimization-problem-be-rewritten-as-a-linear-program&quot;&gt;can be written as a linear program&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finding the sparsest solution (minimizing the &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(l_0\)&lt;/span&gt;-“norm”) is NP-hard. The standard trick is to instead &lt;a href=&quot;https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/abstract/document/1255564&quot;&gt;optimize for the &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(l_1\)&lt;/span&gt;-norm&lt;/a&gt;. But for the problem I’m concerning, I’m optimizing over probability vectors so that is out of the question.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.math.unipd.it/~rinaldi/papers/thesis0.pdf&quot;&gt;Mathematical Programming Methods for Minimizing the Zero-norm over Polyhedral Sets&lt;/a&gt;, Francesco Rinaldi, University of Rome thesis &lt;!-- [[Linear programming in python]](https://stackoverflow.com/a/10705799)  --&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The example pages for&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cvxpy.org/install/index.html&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;cvxpy&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; has a code for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cvxpy.org/examples/applications/sparse_solution.html&quot;&gt;iterative logarithm heuristic&lt;/a&gt; to find a sparse solution. &lt;a href=&quot;#fn1&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot; id=&quot;fnref1&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;media&quot;&gt;Media&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gravity_Research_Foundation&quot;&gt;Gravity Research Foundation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;his wish to overcome gravity dated from the childhood drowning of his sister. “She was unable to fight gravity, which came up and seized her like a dragon and brought her to the bottom,” he wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/the-spike/the-crimes-against-dopamine-b82b082d5f3d&quot;&gt;Dopamine: fast and slow&lt;/a&gt; (Fast spike or inhibition of dopamine signals the (emotionally positive or negative) error between prediction and reality, not reward. Slow dopamine is for wanting, motivation to work, not happiness.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.1843magazine.com/features/the-scientists-who-make-apps-addictive&quot;&gt;The Scientists Who Make Apps Addictive&lt;/a&gt; (B.J. Fogg’s students went on to found Instagram and write books like &lt;em&gt;Hooked: How to Build Habit-Forming Products&lt;/em&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I look at some of my former students and I wonder if they’re really trying to make the world better, or just make money,” said Fogg. “What I always wanted to do was un-enslave people from technology.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Harris was Mike Krieger’s collaborator on Send the Sunshine in Fogg’s class of 2006. Like Krieger, Harris went on to create a real-world app, Apture, which was designed to give instant explanations of complex concepts to online readers […] Harris believed in his mission to explain, yet he could not persuade publishers that incorporating his app would lead to people spending more time on their sites. He came to believe that the internet’s potential to inform and enlighten was at loggerheads with the commercial imperative to seize and hold the attention of users by any means possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After working for Google for a year or so, Harris resigned […] Before leaving, he gave a farewell presentation to Google’s staff in which he argued that they needed to see themselves as moral stewards of the attention of billions of people. Unexpectedly, the slides from his talk became a viral hit inside the company, travelling all the way to the boardroom. Harris was persuaded to stay on and pursue his research at Goo­gle, which created a new job title for him: design ethicist and product philosopher. After a while, Harris realised that although his colleagues were listening politely, they would never take his message seriously without pressure from the outside. He left Google for good earlier this year […]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2019/03/23/sunday-review/human-contact-luxury-screens.html&quot;&gt;Human Contact is Now a Luxury Good&lt;/a&gt;, NY Times&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The bad PowerPoint slide &lt;a href=&quot;https://mcdreeamiemusings.com/new-blog/2019/4/13/gsux1h6bnt8lqjd7w2t2mtvfg81uhx&quot;&gt;that contributes to the Space Shuttle Columbia disaster&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you think you’re in a bad place, your life could be worse if you are &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theverge.com/2019/2/25/18229714/cognizant-facebook-content-moderator-interviews-trauma-working-conditions-arizona&quot;&gt;Facebook moderators&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://slatestarcodex.com/2019/01/01/what-happened-to-90s-environmentalism/&quot;&gt;What happened to 90s environmentalism?&lt;/a&gt;, SSC (Do environmental problems fall out of public consciousness because they have been solved successfully or because they were just a fad all along?)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Insect biomass declines by 75% [&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/insect-ldquo-armageddon-rdquo-5-crucial-questions-answered/&quot;&gt;SA&lt;/a&gt;] [&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2018/11/27/magazine/insect-apocalypse.html&quot;&gt;NYT&lt;/a&gt;] [&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.huffpost.com/entry/nature-destruction-climate-change-world-biodiversity_n_5c49e78ce4b06ba6d3bb2d44?utm_source=politics_fb&amp;amp;utm_campaign=hp_fb_pages&amp;amp;utm_medium=facebook&amp;amp;section=politics&amp;amp;ncid=fcbklnkushpmg00000013&quot;&gt;HuffPost&lt;/a&gt;] [&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2019/jan/15/insect-collapse-we-are-destroying-our-life-support-systems&quot;&gt;Guardian&lt;/a&gt;] (Not sure what to conclude from all these.) &lt;!--    - [Global insect declines: Why aren&#39;t we all dead yet?](https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/KwB9jA9FrsNczWr5F/global-insect-declines-why-aren-t-we-all-dead-yet) --&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://genestogenomes.org/kimura-crow-infinite-alleles/&quot;&gt;Kimura &amp;amp; Crow: Infinite Alleles&lt;/a&gt; (Wanting to “do something in genetics like what the theoretical physicists were doing in physics,” Kimura ended up writing a heat equation obeyed by neutrally-evolved genes.)
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/scitable/topicpage/neutral-theory-the-null-hypothesis-of-molecular-839&quot;&gt;Why should we care about neutral evolution?&lt;/a&gt; (Neutral evolution provides a “null hypothesis”, the background noise to be compared and subtracted to get the signal.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.quantamagazine.org/neutral-theory-of-evolution-challenged-by-evidence-for-dna-selection-20181108/&quot;&gt;An estimate of how much of the human genome undergoes neutral selection&lt;/a&gt;, Quanta (&amp;lt;5% and not all neutral alleles evolve following Kimura’s theory, for example, those that are transmitted through physical mechanism such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Genetic_linkage&quot;&gt;linkage&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.quantamagazine.org/mathematics-shows-how-to-ensure-evolution-20180626/&quot;&gt;Natural selection on weighted graphs&lt;/a&gt;, Quanta&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.quantamagazine.org/the-evolutionary-math-puzzle-20180815/&quot;&gt;The grandmother hypothesis&lt;/a&gt;, Quanta&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/science/2019/mar/28/scientists-find-genetic-mutation-that-makes-woman-feel-no-pain&quot;&gt;Mutations render a woman unable to feel pain or anxiety&lt;/a&gt;. The mutations shut down the gene controlling &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fatty_acid_amide_hydrolase&quot;&gt;FAAH&lt;/a&gt; which breaks down &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anandamide&quot;&gt;anandamide&lt;/a&gt;, a natural cannabis-like substance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Karen Uhlenback is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.quantamagazine.org/karen-uhlenbeck-uniter-of-geometry-and-analysis-wins-abel-prize-20190319/&quot;&gt;the first woman to win the Abel Prize&lt;/a&gt;. (Uhlenback of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ornstein%E2%80%93Uhlenbeck_process&quot;&gt;Ornstein-Uhlenback process&lt;/a&gt; is her father-in-law.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The 1993 article, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.math.uh.edu/~tomforde/Articles/DeathOfProof.pdf&quot;&gt;The Death of Proof&lt;/a&gt; doesn’t age well, and the author knows it: [&lt;a href=&quot;https://blogs.scientificamerican.com/cross-check/the-horgan-surface-and-the-death-of-proof/&quot;&gt;The Horgan Surface and the Death of Proof&lt;/a&gt;] [&lt;a href=&quot;https://blogs.scientificamerican.com/cross-check/okay-maybe-proofs-arent-dying-after-all/&quot;&gt;Okay, Maybe Proofs Aren’t Dying After All&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Corn production is estimated to account for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/sections/thesalt/2019/04/01/708818581/growing-corn-is-a-major-contributor-to-air-pollution-study-finds&quot;&gt;4,300 premature deaths related to air pollution in the US per year&lt;/a&gt;. Ammonia from fertilizer application was by far the largest contributor to corn’s air pollution footprint. 86% of PM2.5 emissions happen on farm&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The 2019 Winter smog in Thailand &lt;a href=&quot;https://towardsdatascience.com/identifying-the-sources-of-winter-air-pollution-in-bangkok-part-ii-72539f9b767a&quot;&gt;seems to correlate most with fire&lt;/a&gt; from as far as 720 km away (Myanmar, Laos and Cambodia)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2019/04/08/the-day-the-dinosaurs-died&quot;&gt;The Day the Dinosaurs Died&lt;/a&gt;, New Yorker&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One day sixty-six million years ago, life on Earth almost came to a shattering end. The world that emerged after the impact was a much simpler place. When sunlight finally broke through the haze, it illuminated a hellish landscape. The oceans were empty. The land was covered with drifting ash. The forests were charred stumps. The cold gave way to extreme heat as a greenhouse effect kicked in. Life mostly consisted of mats of algae and growths of fungus: for years after the impact, the Earth was covered with little other than ferns. Furtive, ratlike mammals lived in the gloomy understory. But eventually life emerged and blossomed again, in new forms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;tl;dr version:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“3 metre problem”: almost no dinosaur remains have before been found 3 metres below the so-called “KT boundary”, a layer of sediment that preserves the asteroid’s debris and ash from the extinction event.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the 70’s, Walter (geologist) and Luis Alvarez (nuclear physicist) discovered a KT layer laced with iridium, conjectured to be from the asteroid impact. The impact crater (named Chicxulub) was found in 1991. The debate was considered largely settled &lt;a href=&quot;http://science.sciencemag.org/content/327/5970/1214&quot;&gt;in 2010&lt;/a&gt; (wow!) that the asteroid caused the extinction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pnas.org/content/early/2019/03/27/1817407116&quot;&gt;The new paper&lt;/a&gt; is a result from the discovery dated back to 2012 by a grad student Robert DePalma of the KT site “Tanis” (a Raiders-of-the-Lost-Ark reference) at Hell Creek in North Dakota. Among the things found are preserved microtektites, a sort of glass beads or spindles that formed from molten rock ejected during the impact and solidified while re-entering the atmosphere. This suggests that the site recorded the first hours or so of the extinction event.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Geophysics problem: there was not enough time for the flood that would preserve the microtektites to reach the site from the source of impact. They conjectured that the flood was caused by seiches that can happen far away from the source, and estimated the time all kinds of different seismic waves would arrive at the site to cause such seiches (6, 10, and 13 minutes).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencemag.org/news/2019/04/astonishment-skepticism-greet-fossils-claimed-record-dinosaur-killing-asteroid-impact&quot;&gt;Skepticism greet fossils claimed to record dinosaur-killing asteroid impact&lt;/a&gt;, ScienceMag&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tax preparation companies lobby Congress to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vox.com/2019/4/9/18301943/last-minute-tax-preparation-h-r-block-turbotax&quot;&gt;ban IRS from creating their own free tax preparation software&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Weighted average of opinions based on prediction track records is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vox.com/future-perfect/2019/4/5/18290870/forecasting-tetlock-prediction-markets-betting&quot;&gt;at least as accurate as prediction markets&lt;/a&gt; (n=535)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/LimbRetrieval-Bot&quot;&gt;You dropped this \&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anime&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A documentary on the CGI animation industry (1/n)
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/wRA8N0R81fc&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;physicsquantummachine-learning&quot;&gt;Physics/quantum/machine learning&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chameleons change their colors by adjusting the osmotic pressure to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/ncomms7368&quot;&gt;change the spacing of Guanine crystals in a lattice&lt;/a&gt;. See also &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Animal_reflectors&quot;&gt;animal reflectors&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Das Sarma on &lt;a href=&quot;https://physicstoday.scitation.org/doi/10.1063/PT.3.4153&quot;&gt;how the scale of unifications in the present day physics is not so grand anymore&lt;/a&gt;, Physics Today&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The 2016 Nobel laureate David Thouless &lt;a href=&quot;https://physicsworld.com/a/topological-physics-pioneer-and-nobel-laureate-david-thouless-dies-at-84&quot;&gt;passes away at 84&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-019-00573-4&quot;&gt;Advanced LIGO+ will have frequency-dependent squeezing&lt;/a&gt;. (“LIGO is already able to spot black holes billions of parsecs away. By 2022, it should detect about one such event per day, and the subsequent ALIGO+ upgrade should push that to one event every few hours.”)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://physicstoday.scitation.org/do/10.1063/PT.6.1.20190411a/full/&quot;&gt;What It Took to Capture a Black Hole&lt;/a&gt;, Physics Todays&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the team was able to resolve superheated plasma streaking just outside the photon orbit radius, the distance from the center of a black hole at which any inward-moving photon no longer has a chance to escape (as opposed to the event horizon, where nothing, regardless of its motion, can escape).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data were from the observing runs all in April 2017. The research team dedicated to imaging was divided into four groups, crunching the data in four different ways. The final image is essential a composite of the four group images “update with higher-quality data”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next observing run in Spring next year should give us the spin of M87*. Meanwhile, the data that we have from observing Sagittarius A*, the black hole at the center of our galaxy, should already be enough to create a similar image. The only things required are “further advances in computational analysis” due to time variation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2019/04/11/science/katie-bouman-black-hole.html&quot;&gt;How Katie Bouman Accidentally Became the Face of the Black Hole Project&lt;/a&gt;, NY Times&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Alán Aspuru-Guzik now has a quantum computing startup &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/alexknapp/2019/04/17/this-startup-just-raised-21-million-to-bring-quantum-computing-to-enterprise-applications/&quot;&gt;Zapata Computing&lt;/a&gt;. (He &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thecrimson.com/article/2018/3/30/chem-prof-to-canada/&quot;&gt;left Harvard for Toronto&lt;/a&gt; last year.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Michael Nielsen’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://quantum.country/search/&quot;&gt;spaced-repetition based pedagogical article&lt;/a&gt; on Grover’s search algorithm&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://physicstoday.scitation.org/doi/10.1063/PT.3.4164&quot;&gt;Machine learning in many-body quantum physics and quantum ML algorithms&lt;/a&gt;, recommended.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1903.10563&quot;&gt;Machine learning and the physical sciences&lt;/a&gt; 1903.10563 (review article)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2019/03/27/technology/turing-award-ai.html&quot;&gt;Geoffrey Hinton, Yann LeCun and Yoshua Bengio&lt;/a&gt; won the Turing Award.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Book of Why&lt;/em&gt;, Pearl and Mackenzie 2018 [A &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/2483026514?book_show_action=true&amp;amp;from_review_page=1&quot;&gt;critical review&lt;/a&gt; on Goodreads]
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.inference.vc/untitled/&quot;&gt;ML beyond Curve Fitting: An Intro to Causal Inference and do-Calculus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;meditation&quot;&gt;Meditation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Meditation as predictive processing, a comment on &lt;a href=&quot;https://slatestarcodex.com/2017/09/20/meditative-states-as-mental-feedback-loops/#comment-549013&quot;&gt;Meditative States as Mental Feedback Loops&lt;/a&gt;, SSC
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://link.springer.com/article/10.3758/BF03200092&quot;&gt;An approach through the looking-glass&lt;/a&gt;, Hershberger 1986&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://opentheory.net/2018/12/the-neuroscience-of-meditation/&quot;&gt;The Neuroscience of Meditation: Four Models&lt;/a&gt; (Buddhism, Predictive coding (“free-energy principle”), Connectome-specific harmonic waves, Neural annealing)
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mindcoolness.com/blog/bayesian-brain-predictive-processing/&quot;&gt;The Bayesian Brain: An Introduction to Predictive Processing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/M4w2rdYgCKctbADMn/sequence-introduction-non-agent-and-multiagent-models-of&quot;&gt;Sequence introduction: non-agent and multiagent models of mind&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/AhcEaqWYpa2NieNsK/subagents-introspective-awareness-and-blending&quot;&gt;Subagents, introspective awareness, and blending&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lesswrong.com/s/ZbmRyDN8TCpBTZSip/p/oJwJzeZ6ar2Hr7KAX&quot;&gt;Subagents, akrasia, and coherence in humans&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;musics&quot;&gt;Musics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLj3Mg9WXbXd9MeOuI15OCw4xMvK4BKlIS&quot;&gt;Great covers of almost every Mega Man X5 and X6 theme&lt;/a&gt; by Lenny Lederman&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;touhou&quot;&gt;Touhou&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4vegkBjpO9A&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;+&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qcSVPCWCPbk&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt; hours of Touhou trance remixes by D-514&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kSjVejxBI-g&quot;&gt;邪な炎&lt;/a&gt; (Solar Sect of Mystic Wisdom ~ Nuclear Fusion), &lt;a href=&quot;http://butaotome.com/2018/c95/&quot;&gt;Abyss&lt;/a&gt; (C95), BUTAOTOME&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SxaS9KWCBNw&quot;&gt;Tick-Tock Anthology&lt;/a&gt; (Kid’s Festival ~ Innocent Treasures &amp;amp; Gensokyo The Gods Loved), &lt;a href=&quot;https://huringcatmark.booth.pm/items/364619&quot;&gt;Baby Little City&lt;/a&gt; (C90), Fuling Cat Mark (Genre: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shibuya-kei&quot;&gt;Shibuya-Kei&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;manga&quot;&gt;Manga&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://myanimelist.net/manga/96792/Kimetsu_no_Yaiba&quot;&gt;Kimetsu no Yaiba&lt;/a&gt; (Chapter 20 - 58), Gotouge Koyoharu (One of the manga &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/HunterXHunter/comments/5ggzud/the_3_manga_togashi_recommends/&quot;&gt;recommended by Togashi Yoshihiro&lt;/a&gt;, the other two being Gunjou no Magmel and EX-ARM&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;anime&quot;&gt;Anime&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://myanimelist.net/anime/12189/Hyouka&quot;&gt;Hyouka&lt;/a&gt; (22 Episodes), Kyoto Animation {Honezawa Yonobu} [Novel] 2012 (Notable episodes: 17, 21)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://myanimelist.net/anime/37510/Mob_Psycho_100_II&quot;&gt;Mob Psycho 100 II&lt;/a&gt; (13 Episodes), Bones {ONE} [Webmanga] 2019&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://myanimelist.net/anime/5081/Bakemonogatari&quot;&gt;Bakemonogatari&lt;/a&gt; (15 Episodes), Shaft {Nisio Isin} [Light novels] 2009, 2010 &lt;em&gt;(Rewatch)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;video-games&quot;&gt;Video games&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://store.steampowered.com/app/851100/Touhou_Luna_Nights/&quot;&gt;Touhou Luna Nights&lt;/a&gt;, Team Ladybug&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pros:&lt;/em&gt; Great pixel art and attentions to details. A number of objects interacts with time manipulation. (Yes, you play as Sakuya.) The water physics is especially cool. &lt;em&gt;Cons:&lt;/em&gt; Snail Time and the grace mechanics makes the game really easy, in addition to the short length and the map not sprawling enough for a Metroidvania, which reminds me that I haven’t finished &lt;a href=&quot;https://store.steampowered.com/app/400910/RabiRibi/&quot;&gt;Rabi-Ribi&lt;/a&gt;. That one has a wondrous, sprawling map (and in a sense a funny comparison because it is a bullet hell game while Luna Nights is not.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;!-- [Mob Psycho 100 II](https://myanimelist.net/anime/37510/Mob_Psycho_100_II) (13 Episodes), Bones {ONE} [Webmanga] 2019 (Technically the last episode aired on April 1st, but whatever.)

  Both are excellent coming-of-age stories. --&gt;

&lt;section class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn1&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;cvxpy&lt;/code&gt; needs Microsoft Visual C++ 14.0. Go and download &lt;a href=&quot;https://visualstudio.microsoft.com/downloads/#build-tools-for-visual-studio-2017&quot;&gt;Visual Studio 2019 (16.0) (Community)&lt;/a&gt;. Open the installer and &lt;a href=&quot;https://stackoverflow.com/questions/29846087/microsoft-visual-c-14-0-is-required-unable-to-find-vcvarsall-bat&quot;&gt;check “Desktop Development with C++”&lt;/a&gt;. To be safe, also upgrade the &lt;code&gt;setuptools&lt;/code&gt; with &lt;code&gt;pip install --upgrade setuptools&lt;/code&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>February 2019 Archive</title>
   <link href="/feb-2019-log.html"/>
   <updated>2019-03-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>h/feb-2019-log</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is an archive of what I found useful, interesting, or simply enjoyable from February 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;toc&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;research&quot;&gt;Research&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;quantum-state-verification&quot;&gt;Quantum state verification&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4021&quot;&gt;Why are amplitudes complex?&lt;/a&gt;, Shtetl-Optimized (An update on Scott’s personal conundrum)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the quantum foundations community, it is popular to derive the complex amplitudes (as opposed to real or quaternionic) from the “local tomography” principle &lt;a href=&quot;#fn1&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot; id=&quot;fnref1&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; which Scott has never found intuitive. Now he stumbles upon the following question:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;suppose we have a two-outcome measurement &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(E\)&lt;/span&gt; (let’s say, on &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(n\)&lt;/span&gt; qubits), and suppose it accepts every product state with the same probability &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(p\)&lt;/span&gt;. Must &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(E\)&lt;/span&gt; then accept every entangled state with probability &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(p\)&lt;/span&gt; as well? Or, a closely-related question: suppose we know &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(E\)&lt;/span&gt;’s acceptance probabilities on every product state. Is that enough to determine its acceptance probabilities on all &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(n\)&lt;/span&gt;-qubit states?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer is that, yes, the acceptance probabilities are determined and, in fact, constant for all states. This follows from a result in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/quant-ph/9811018&quot;&gt;Braunstein et al 1999&lt;/a&gt;, specifically that there is always a ball of constant size around the maximally mixed state, all states in which are separable. This is in fact true only if amplitudes are complex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, to disprove the statement “the acceptance probabilities are constant for all states” when it is false requires knowing the acceptance probabilities on product states to exponential accuracy. A non-example of the statement to illustrate this: the measurement projecting an &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(n\)&lt;/span&gt;-qubit state onto &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(n/2\)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bell_state&quot;&gt;Bell pairs&lt;/a&gt; accepts every product state with exponentially small probability (but the probabilities are different for different product states) even though it accepts &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(n\)&lt;/span&gt; Bell pairs with probability 1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quotable: “quantum mechanics over the quaternions is a &lt;strong&gt;flaming garbage fire&lt;/strong&gt;”.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1705.06719&quot;&gt;Single-copy entanglement detection&lt;/a&gt;, Dimić and Dakić 2018 (The idea of a test in which the acceptance probability for product states falls off exponentially can be used to detect entanglement.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1709.03353&quot;&gt;Optimal verification of entangled states with local measurements&lt;/a&gt;, Pallister, Linden, and Montanaro 2018&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verification “is the state &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\ket{\psi}\)&lt;/span&gt;?” is easier than tomography. Given a state &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\sigma\)&lt;/span&gt;, we want to know if it is “closed” to &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\ket{\psi}\)&lt;/span&gt; so that we can accept or otherwise reject it. This can also be phrased as a promise problem: either the given state &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\sigma\)&lt;/span&gt; is the true state &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\ket{\psi}\)&lt;/span&gt; or &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\av{\psi|\sigma|\psi} \le 1 - \epsilon\)&lt;/span&gt;. The quantity &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(1 - \epsilon\)&lt;/span&gt; is the (&lt;em&gt;test-independent&lt;/em&gt;) worst case fidelity that we’re willing to accept.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors consider a binary hypothesis testing that disallows &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Type_I_and_type_II_errors&quot;&gt;type I error&lt;/a&gt; (rejecting the true state) while having a minimum type-II error probability &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\delta_n\)&lt;/span&gt;, possibly depending on &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(n\)&lt;/span&gt;. Their argument goes as follows: suppose that the test has the probability &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(p\)&lt;/span&gt; of accepting the true state and &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(p-\Delta_{\epsilon}\)&lt;/span&gt; of accepting a wrong state. Then our task is to distinguish between Bernoulli trials drawn from i.i.d. distributions &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\{p,1-p\}\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\{p-\Delta_{\epsilon}, 1-(p-\Delta_{\epsilon})\}\)&lt;/span&gt;. The Chernoff-Stein lemma says that &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\[ \lim_{n\to\infty} \frac{\delta_n}{n} = - D(p||p-\Delta_{\epsilon}), \]&lt;/span&gt; where &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(D(Q||P)\)&lt;/span&gt; is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Relative_entropy&quot;&gt;relative entropy&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\[ D(Q||P) = \sum_x Q(x) \log \frac{Q(x)}{P(x)}.  \]&lt;/span&gt; Rearranging the equation, we get a bound on the number of samples &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\[ n \ge \frac{\ln \delta^{-1}}{D(p||p-\Delta_{\epsilon})}. \]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They argue that the “worst case” scaling of &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(D(p||p-\Delta_{\epsilon})\)&lt;/span&gt; is quadratic in &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\Delta_{\epsilon}\)&lt;/span&gt; because infinitesimally the relative entropy is just the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fisher_information_metric&quot;&gt;Fisher information metric&lt;/a&gt;, which scales as the square of the distance &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\sum_x \Delta^2_{\epsilon}/4p\)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fn2&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot; id=&quot;fnref2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, whereas setting &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(p=1\)&lt;/span&gt; gives you a linear scaling across all values of &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\Delta_{\epsilon}\)&lt;/span&gt;. (Small &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\Delta_{\epsilon}\)&lt;/span&gt; makes it hard to distinguish the two distributions but we probably expect it to be small in practice, both in adversarial and non-adversarial scenarios.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given all that, the task of finding an optimal verification scheme is reduced to minimizing the probability of accepting the “worst” wrong state (easiest to have us fooled) &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\[ \min_{\Omega} \max_{\substack{\sigma \\ \av{\psi|\sigma|\psi} \le 1 - \epsilon}} \Tr (\Omega \sigma) := 1-\Delta_{\epsilon} \]&lt;/span&gt; over the “test operator” &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\Omega = \sum_j \mu_j P_j\)&lt;/span&gt;, a convex sum of all the tests &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(P_j\)&lt;/span&gt; with eigenvalue 1 for the target state. The (&lt;em&gt;test-dependent&lt;/em&gt;) &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\delta\)&lt;/span&gt; is no worse than the worst case error &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\((1-\Delta_{\epsilon})^n\)&lt;/span&gt;, thus giving &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\[ n \ge \frac{\ln \delta^{-1}}{\ln (1-\Delta_{\epsilon})^{-1}} \approx \frac{\ln \delta^{-1}}{\Delta_{\epsilon}}, \]&lt;/span&gt; where we have assumed &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\Delta_{\epsilon}\)&lt;/span&gt; to be small again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following paper shows that &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\Delta_{\epsilon}\)&lt;/span&gt;, which determines the efficiency of the test, is linearly related to the worst case fidelity &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\epsilon\)&lt;/span&gt;, the proportionality constant being the gap between two largest eigenvalues of &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\Omega\)&lt;/span&gt;. The paper also explores the adversarial scenario, in which case all eigenvalues matter, not just the second largest one. All in all, I need to read more of it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1806.05565&quot;&gt;Efficient verification of pure quantum states with applications to hypergraph states&lt;/a&gt;, Zhu and Hayashi 1806.05565&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Pallister paper gives the optimal local measurement for all two-qubit pure states and optimal &lt;em&gt;stabilizer&lt;/em&gt; measurements for all &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(n\)&lt;/span&gt;-qubit stabilizer states: &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\Delta_{\epsilon}\approx \epsilon/2\)&lt;/span&gt; for measuring all stabilizer operators and &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\epsilon/n\)&lt;/span&gt; for measuring only a set of stabilizer generators.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1808.10786&quot;&gt;Validating and certifying stabilizer states&lt;/a&gt;, Kalev and Kyrillidis 1808.10786&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1104.4695&quot;&gt;Direct fidelity estimation&lt;/a&gt; is great because it doesn’t matter how many qubits you want to verify, the number of samples stay the same. However, it is also not great &lt;em&gt;by the same reason&lt;/em&gt;; even though all we have now are on the order of 10-100 qubits, you still need the same number of samples as if you have a thousand of qubits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem considered by the current paper is in a sense opposite to that in the Pallister paper. in the Pallister paper, we are given the worst case fidelity &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\epsilon\)&lt;/span&gt; and are asked to find an optimal measurement, whereas in this paper we are given a (stabilizer) measurement and are asked for the worst case fidelity &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(1-\epsilon\)&lt;/span&gt; to a desired stabilizer state. The latter can be done with &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(n^3\ln(2\delta^{-1})/2r^2\)&lt;/span&gt; samples, where &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(r\)&lt;/span&gt; is the radius away from &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(1-\epsilon\)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;representation-theory&quot;&gt;Representation theory&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://qinf.fisica.unimi.it/~paris/PDF/displa.pdf&quot;&gt;Displacement operator by beam splitter&lt;/a&gt;, Paris 1996&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How to implement a displacement operator (a Heisenberg group element) &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\[ D(\alpha) = \exp(\alpha b\dgg - \alpha^* b) \]&lt;/span&gt; on an arbitrary quantum state using an auxillary laser mode and a beam splitter (a symplectic group element)? The beam splitter unitary &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\[ \mathrm{BS} = \exp \left[ i \tan^{-1} \sqrt{\frac{1-\tau}{\tau}} (ab\dgg + a\dgg b) \right] \]&lt;/span&gt; looks almost like a displacement operator, if only we could replace &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(a\)&lt;/span&gt; by &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\alpha\)&lt;/span&gt; and flip the sign. Here comes a cool trick: notice that &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(ab\dgg\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(a\dgg b\)&lt;/span&gt; are respectively the raising and lowering operator in &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\sl(2)\)&lt;/span&gt; made out of Schwinger’s bosons. (&lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(a\dgg a - b\dgg b\)&lt;/span&gt; is &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(Z\)&lt;/span&gt;.) So I can do the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.encyclopediaofmath.org/index.php/Gauss_decomposition&quot;&gt;Gauss decomposition&lt;/a&gt; to move the exponentials of &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(ab\dgg\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(a\dgg b\)&lt;/span&gt; to the left and the right, where &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\bra{z}\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\ket{z}\)&lt;/span&gt; are waiting to turn &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(b\)&lt;/span&gt; into &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(z\)&lt;/span&gt;. This gives (barred some mistake) &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\[ \av{z|\mathrm{BS}|z} = \exp (\beta a\dgg a/2) \otimes \exp (\xi z^* b) \exp(-\beta b\dgg b/2) \exp (-\xi^* zb\dgg) \]&lt;/span&gt; Then rotate the linear term by the quadratic Hamiltonian &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\beta b\dgg b/4\)&lt;/span&gt; before taking the appropriate limits to obtain the result.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Representation Theory and Complex Geometry&lt;/em&gt;, Chriss and Ginzburg&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Borel-Weil theorem in Peter Woit’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.math.columbia.edu/~woit/LieGroups-2013/&quot;&gt;lectures&lt;/a&gt; (Old lectures 13-16)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Associated to each weight &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\lambda\)&lt;/span&gt; under a maximal torus &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(T\)&lt;/span&gt; is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Line_bundle&quot;&gt;line bundle&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(L_{\lambda}\)&lt;/span&gt; over the base space &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(G/T\)&lt;/span&gt; (the line is the one-dimensional irrep &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(e^{\lambda(H)}\)&lt;/span&gt; of &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(T\)&lt;/span&gt;, thinking of the weight &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\lambda\)&lt;/span&gt; as a linear functional on &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\h\)&lt;/span&gt;) and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ncatlab.org/nlab/show/space+of+sections&quot;&gt;space of sections&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\Gamma (G/T,L_{\lambda})\)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Borel-Weil theorem gives every irrep of a semisimple Lie group (or an algebraic group) over &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\C\)&lt;/span&gt; a concrete realization as a subspace of &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\Gamma (G/T,L_{\lambda})\)&lt;/span&gt;. As an &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Induced_representation#Geometric&quot;&gt;induced representation&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\Gamma (G/T,L_{\lambda})\)&lt;/span&gt; has the isotypic decomposition &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\[ \Gamma(G/T,L_{\lambda}) = \bigoplus_{\mu} V_{\mu} \otimes (V_{\mu}^*)_{-\lambda}, \]&lt;/span&gt; where &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\((V^*_{\mu})_{-\lambda}\)&lt;/span&gt; is the &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(-\lambda\)&lt;/span&gt;-weight space of &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(V_{\mu}^*\)&lt;/span&gt;. (The minus sign comes about because we’re acting on &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(V^*_{\mu}\)&lt;/span&gt;.) We could single out the irrep &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(V_{\lambda}\)&lt;/span&gt; by putting in by hand the condition that &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(-\lambda\)&lt;/span&gt; has to be a lowest weight, or equivalently, &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\lambda\)&lt;/span&gt; has to be a highest weight &lt;a href=&quot;#fn3&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot; id=&quot;fnref3&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. What is beautiful about the Borel-Weil theorem is that this condition has a simple meaning in complex geometry (no pun intended): the sections have to be &lt;em&gt;holomorphic&lt;/em&gt; for the following reason. The tangent space of &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(G/T\)&lt;/span&gt; at the identity is isomorphic to the even-dimensional Lie algebra of negative and positive roots consisting of &lt;em&gt;holomorphic&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;antiholomorphic&lt;/em&gt; vectors: &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\[\begin{align}
     E_{\alpha} = \frac{\partial}{\partial z_{\alpha}}, &amp;amp;&amp;amp; E_{-\alpha} = \frac{\partial}{\partial \overline{z}_{\alpha}}.
 \end{align}\]&lt;/span&gt; But &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(-\lambda\)&lt;/span&gt; is a lowest weight iff the corresponding section &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(f\)&lt;/span&gt; is annihilated by &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(E_{-\alpha}\)&lt;/span&gt; for all positive roots &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\alpha\)&lt;/span&gt;. In other words, &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(f\)&lt;/span&gt; is a holomorphic function.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\SU(2)\)&lt;/span&gt; example is given in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.math.columbia.edu/~woit/notes16.pdf&quot;&gt;Lecture 16&lt;/a&gt;, in which case the space of sections are homogeneous polynomials of degree &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(k\)&lt;/span&gt; in two variables, a standard textbook result.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MO threads on &lt;a href=&quot;https://mathoverflow.net/questions/74796/complex-structure-on-flag-manifolds&quot;&gt;complex&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://mathoverflow.net/questions/45004/kahler-structure-on-flag-manifolds&quot;&gt;Kählerian&lt;/a&gt; flag manifolds (Why are flag manifolds important to physicists? They exhaust all the possibilities of compact homogeneous Kähler manifolds associated with &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(G\)&lt;/span&gt; connected, compact, and semisimple.)
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Flag Manifolds, Alekseevsky 1996 (11th Yugoslav Geometric Seminar)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trying to trace the history of &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(G/T \cong G^{\C}/B\)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pnas.org/content/40/12/1147&quot;&gt;Kählerian Coset Spaces of Semisimple Lie Groups&lt;/a&gt;, Borel 1954&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.numdam.org/item/?id=SB_1951-1954__2__447_0&quot;&gt;Représentations linéaires et espaces homogènes kählériens des groupes de Lie compacts&lt;/a&gt;, Serre 1954&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lie Groups&lt;/em&gt;, Duistermaat and Kolk 2000&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;media&quot;&gt;Media&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.decisionproblem.com/paperclips&quot;&gt;game&lt;/a&gt; you play as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.lesswrong.com/wiki/Paperclip_maximizer&quot;&gt;paperclip maximizer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bbc.com/future/story/20190218-are-we-on-the-road-to-civilisation-collapse&quot;&gt;Are we on the road to civilization collapse?&lt;/a&gt;, BBC
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reconciling taxon senescence with the Red Queen’s hypothesis, Žliobaitė, Fortelius and Stenseth (Random walk with resource constraint often produces the observed unimodal trajectory of civilization growth) &lt;!-- By 2005 (total population: 6.5 billions), [an estimate](https://www.vistawide.com/languages/top_30_languages.htm) of 510 millions people speak English while 60 millions (~ total population of Thailand) speak Thai. Thus, writing in English increases the number of potential readerships 8.5 times. --&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1806.02404&quot;&gt;Dissolving the Fermi paradox&lt;/a&gt;, Sandberg, Drexler and Ord [&lt;a href=&quot;https://aleph.se/andart2/space/seti/dissolving-the-fermi-paradox/&quot;&gt;Sandberg himself&lt;/a&gt;] [&lt;a href=&quot;https://slatestarcodex.com/2018/07/03/ssc-journal-club-dissolving-the-fermi-paradox/&quot;&gt;SSC&lt;/a&gt;] [&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/MdGp3vs2butANB7zX/the-fermi-paradox-what-did-sandberg-drexler-and-ord-really&quot;&gt;LW&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;GPT-2: &lt;a href=&quot;https://d4mucfpksywv.cloudfront.net/better-language-models/language_models_are_unsupervised_multitask_learners.pdf&quot;&gt;Language Models are Unsupervised Multitask Learners&lt;/a&gt;, Radford et al. 2019 [OpenAI &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.openai.com/better-language-models/&quot;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt;]
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vox.com/future-perfect/2019/2/14/18222270/artificial-intelligence-open-ai-natural-language-processing&quot;&gt;An AI helped us write this article&lt;/a&gt;, Vox&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://slatestarcodex.com/2019/02/18/do-neural-nets-dream-of-electric-hobbits/&quot;&gt;Do Neural Nets Dream of Electric Hobbits?&lt;/a&gt;, SSC&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://slatestarcodex.com/2019/02/19/gpt-2-as-step-toward-general-intelligence/&quot;&gt;GPT-2 as Step Toward General Intelligence&lt;/a&gt;, SSC&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://approximatelycorrect.com/2019/02/17/openai-trains-language-model-mass-hysteria-ensues/&quot;&gt;OpenAI Trains Language Model, Mass Hysteria Ensues&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thoughtco.com/cat-history-and-domestication-170651&quot;&gt;The history of human-cat co-existence&lt;/a&gt;, ThoughtCo. &lt;!-- A federal judge rules [male-only draft violates constitution](https://www.npr.org/2019/02/25/697622930/judge-rules-male-only-draft-violates-constitution). --&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Manfred Eigen of the ultrafast-chemical-reaction and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quasispecies_model&quot;&gt;quasispecies&lt;/a&gt; fame &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/local/obituaries/manfred-eigen-nobel-winning-chemist-who-clocked-the-speeds-of-fast-reactions-dies-at-91/2019/02/10/d9c69136-2c21-11e9-984d-9b8fba003e81_story.html?noredirect=on&amp;amp;utm_term=.a8b07db017c4&quot;&gt;passed away&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All Impossible Foods partner restaurants will have the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.engadget.com/2019/01/07/impossible-burger-2&quot;&gt;meat-free burgers 2.0 that taste like real meat&lt;/a&gt; by mid-March.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://slatestarcodex.com/2016/02/20/writing-advice/&quot;&gt;Nonfiction Writing Advice&lt;/a&gt;, SSC&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thailand’s debate on paraquat ban: [&lt;a href=&quot;https://themomentum.co/paraquat-is-still-being-allowed-in-thailand&quot;&gt;The Momentum&lt;/a&gt;] [&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/biothai.net/photos/a.467826533255873/2177002662338243/?type=3&amp;amp;__xts__%5B0%5D=68.ARCYltyWKIItwUPCJ1ECDJtYXvAtg2_PfXYhfGxpTHv8fmzpJgGlhLIuR73FbV0yhOplJMmnxGj1JdUhnl4KvCrllykgvFnxQATCenzaXN95rd_C5VOJj_siedtDBJFTgONLr_8LSwT16qmx1j842TaPeeMLrWXNESeK3PA795e3sNgddJjNTWzk8dxQT5RSnKFXQCmzQDJ-bM7FMLgNCyfqPoxXztUqf3MYkIjb1Ot-2OWgbl7ECkO1NSySs_b6YxX6LxrbsN06CXJrGBbQmrvxNsRyCgVDQAwsKZqht0KBKAWZJ1sOgqbC39t956mIJnWO0_Dos2Dl4VSXExh7&amp;amp;__tn__=H-R&quot;&gt;BIOTHAI&lt;/a&gt;] (ภาษาไทย)&lt;/p&gt;
There seems to be an exaggeration regarding paraquat contamination in soil and water. This doesn’t undermine arguments for banning paraquat, but we should be mindful not to oversimplify research findings in order to support our position.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.chemistryworld.com/podcasts/paraquat/8124.article&quot;&gt;Brian Clegg&lt;/a&gt;, Chemistry World (“environmentally-based decision is anything but black and white”)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://pmep.cce.cornell.edu/profiles/extoxnet/metiram-propoxur/paraquat-ext.html&quot;&gt;A Pesticide Information Project&lt;/a&gt;, 1993&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cdpr.ca.gov/docs/emon/pubs/fatememo/paraquat_final.pdf&quot;&gt;Environmental fate and ecotoxicology of paraquat: a California perspective&lt;/a&gt;, Sartori and Vidrio 2018&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spiral patterns in hallucinations &lt;a href=&quot;https://plus.maths.org/content/uncoiling-spiral-maths-and-hallucinations&quot;&gt;reflect physiological structure in the visual system&lt;/a&gt;, PBS math&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thiswaifudoesnotexist.net/index.html&quot;&gt;This Waifu Does not Exist&lt;/a&gt; (The anime version of &lt;a href=&quot;https://thispersondoesnotexist.com/&quot;&gt;This Person Does not Exist&lt;/a&gt;, a StyleGAN face generator)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2018/12/17/science/donald-knuth-computers-algorithms-programming.html&quot;&gt;The Yoda of Silicon Valley&lt;/a&gt;, NY Times&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://augmentingcognition.com/ltm.html&quot;&gt;Augmenting long-term memory&lt;/a&gt;, Nielsen&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anki isn’t just a tool for memorizing simple facts. It’s a tool for understanding almost anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You should read 10 most important papers of a field to pick up open problems, questions that you’d personally like answered, tricks, curious observations that seem important, and sometimes even field-wide blind spots.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Avoid Ankify intellectually interesting but emotionally dried facts that are so removed from everything else you know (“orphan questions”), which will feel pointless to remember after a while. Find something related to personal projects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meditation&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0079612318301596?via%3Dihub&quot;&gt;The neuroscience of meditation: classification, phenomenology, correlates, and mechanisms&lt;/a&gt;, Brandmeyer, Delorme and Wahbehdf 2019&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3146707/&quot;&gt;On the Relationship Between the Practice of Mindfulness Meditation and Personality—an Exploratory Analysis of the Mediating Role of Mindfulness Skills&lt;/a&gt;, van den Hurk et al. 2011&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anime&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A Carnival Phantasm &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nicovideo.jp/watch/sm34624137&quot;&gt;Touhou parody&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;physicsquantum&quot;&gt;Physics/quantum&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/gifs/comments/arhwhf/pen_ink_on_a_leaf_zooming_through_a_puddle/&quot;&gt;Ink propulsion engine&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#39;https://gfycat.com/ifr/FoolhardySoupyKoi&#39; frameborder=&#39;0&#39; scrolling=&#39;no&#39; allowfullscreen width=&#39;309&#39; height=&#39;500&#39;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pnas.org/content/early/2019/02/13/1818350116&quot;&gt;Linking plasma formation in grapes to microwave resonances of aqueous dimers&lt;/a&gt;, Khattak, Bianucci and Slepkov 2019 (Two grapes touching at a point &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wired.com/story/why-a-grape-turns-into-a-fireball-in-a-microwave/&quot;&gt;create a plasma ball&lt;/a&gt; inside a microwave because wet, grape-sized objects sustains and amplifies standing microwaves, focusing the energy into a single point.) &lt;!-- - [inordinatum](https://inordinatum.wordpress.com), a blog on physics and maths of stochastic processes
        - [Stochastic processes II](http://galton.uchicago.edu/~lalley/Courses/313/), University of Chicago, Steven Lalley --&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Daniel Harlow’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/daniel.harlow.31/posts/10104284984149212&quot;&gt;Facebook discussion&lt;/a&gt; on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2019/01/23/opinion/particle-physics-large-hadron-collider.htm&quot;&gt;NY Times piece&lt;/a&gt; by Sabine Hossenfelder. I agree with one of the comments that there are at least two social consequences of not building a next-generation collider that are tangled together (1) punishing theorists (because science is not self-correcting) for not learning from their mistakes and hyping a next-generation collider up for a wrong reason (2) punishing experimentalists for the mistakes made by theorists (which we don’t want).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Someone wrote a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mustythoughts.com/jekyll/update/2019/01/12/how-I-got-a-job-in-QC.html&quot;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; on what he did to get a job in quantum computing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Andy Matuschak and Michael Nielsen &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/QuantumComputing/comments/anawy4/alpha_testers_needed_for_quantum_computing_for/&quot;&gt;recruit alpha testers&lt;/a&gt; for spaced-repetition-based “Quantum Computing for the Very Curious”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.physicsforums.com/threads/find-your-ideal-quantum-interpretation.966905/&quot;&gt;Find your ideal quantum interpretation.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wired.co.uk/article/quantum-game-jam-finland-helsinki&quot;&gt;Quantum Game Jam&lt;/a&gt; at Helsinki&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://jila.colorado.edu/qip2019/program.html&quot;&gt;QIP 2019 videos&lt;/a&gt; are now online.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.technologyreview.com/s/612596/the-man-turning-china-into-a-quantum-superpower/&quot;&gt;Pan Jianwei&lt;/a&gt; in MIT Techonology Review: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.technologyreview.com/magazine/2019/01/&quot;&gt;The China Issue&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1902.02332&quot;&gt;Quantum cryptanalysis of symmetric, public-key and hash-based cryptographic schemes&lt;/a&gt;, Vlad Gheorghiu and Michele Mosca&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roughly speaking, the &lt;em&gt;physical footprint&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(nq\)&lt;/span&gt; is a space resource and the &lt;em&gt;quantum security parameter&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(qs\)&lt;/span&gt; is a time resource. &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(nq\)&lt;/span&gt; is the number of qubits per CPU parallelizing Grover’s search, the best known quantum attack against symmetric cryptographic protocols and hash functions. &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(qs\)&lt;/span&gt; in this case is the number of surface code cycles, assuming that fault tolerence is achieved via the surface code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Breaking RSA and ECC schemes in 24 hours may require at least ten million qubits, &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(10^{11}\)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(T\)&lt;/span&gt; gates, and &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(10^{13}\)&lt;/span&gt; cycles. Symmetric schemes may require &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(&amp;gt;2^{100}\)&lt;/span&gt; cycles to break.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;musics&quot;&gt;Musics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FB42AqX2wlM&quot;&gt;March of the Spirits&lt;/a&gt;, Imaginary Force, Bob Katsionis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Marble Machine, Wintergatan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/IvUU8joBb1Q?controls=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;!-- [Elixir](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=C91bls9Wm84), Loudspeaker, Marty Friedman --&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;finnish-power-metal&quot;&gt;Finnish &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Power_metal&quot;&gt;power metal&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;!--
&quot;Classic&quot; Sonata Arctica AKA power metal before 2007 (Jani the guitarist also left the band in 2007. Cause or coincidence? Jani was [recruited by Altaria and later formed his own band Cain&#39;s Offering](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_power_metal_bands). The latter has released two albums so far: Gather the Faithful (2009) and Stormcrow (2015).)
- [Happiest power metal](https://www.reddit.com/r/PowerMetal/comments/25gpwu/happiest_power_metal_you_know/), reddit --&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sonata Arctica
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Gl1z5fuFnCg&quot;&gt;UnOpened&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=48-z85QquO8&quot;&gt;Destruction Preventer&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oen3-gC-paI&quot;&gt;Ecliptica&lt;/a&gt; 1999&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ahjMrcHAVaw&quot;&gt;Weballergy&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=VA0IAbizUfg&quot;&gt;San Sebastian&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pMVJsAZrodA&quot;&gt;Black Sheep&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5yszaOJHPjA&quot;&gt;Wolf &amp;amp; Raven&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=G0NRdc9lm6g&quot;&gt;Silence&lt;/a&gt; 2001&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_nzwF3j4Gg4&quot;&gt;The Cage&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ek7jUrVK04w&quot;&gt;Winterheart’s Guild&lt;/a&gt; 2003&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stratovarius
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=N2l8KtdQ7Ek&quot;&gt;Hunting High and Low&lt;/a&gt;, Infinite 2000&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CCnn7WEQIDI&quot;&gt;Eagleheart&lt;/a&gt;, Elements Pt. 1 2002&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bxegqv87JhA&quot;&gt;Father Time&lt;/a&gt;, Episode 2010&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Similarity/homage&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Dngwio0eJS0&quot;&gt;Rising Force&lt;/a&gt;, Yngwie Malmsteen {&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_k27dYN8eCY&quot;&gt;Rising Scarlet&lt;/a&gt; (東方緋想天), THUNDER CONCERTO (C75), IRON ATTACK}&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=o8p4raXEQLU&quot;&gt;Back in the Village&lt;/a&gt;, Iron Maiden {&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Dn4zUG6O2lU&quot;&gt;Suck a Sage&lt;/a&gt;, Ishiwatari Daisuke}&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;section class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn1&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/quant-ph/0101012&quot;&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/quant-ph/0104088&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, for example&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn2&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Note that while the relative entropy is asymmetric, the Fisher information is symmetric and thus is a true distance function.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref2&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn3&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;A potential point of confusion: The highest weight of &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(V_{\lambda}^*\)&lt;/span&gt; is generally not &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(-\lambda\)&lt;/span&gt;; we need to map the negative weight to the positive, highest weight by an element of the Weyl group (called the “longest element”). Here we only need the fact that &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(-\lambda\)&lt;/span&gt; is the lowest weight of &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(V_{\lambda}^*\)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref3&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>January 2019 Archive</title>
   <link href="/jan-2019-log.html"/>
   <updated>2019-02-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>h/jan-2019-log</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is an archive of what I found useful, interesting, or simply enjoyable from January 2019 (and a bit from December 2018).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;toc&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;research&quot;&gt;Research&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;generalized-coherent-states&quot;&gt;Generalized coherent states&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.aps.org/rmp/abstract/10.1103/RevModPhys.62.867&quot;&gt;Coherent states: Theory and some applications [paywalled]&lt;/a&gt;, Zhang, Feng and Gilmore 1990&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The paper talks about group generalizations of the notion of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coherent_states&quot;&gt;coherent states&lt;/a&gt;, mainly of Perelomov and Gilmore. Naturally, it briefly mentions other approaches but is quick to point out their drawbacks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type=&quot;1&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Coherent states as eigenstates of lowering operators&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[…] the adoption of this definition […] has two major drawbacks, the first mathematical and the second physical: (a) Coherent states cannot be defined in Hilbert spaces of finite dimensionality in this way. In particular, this would preclude the construction of coherent states for compact Lie groups (Perelomov, 1972). Furthermore, states defined in this way have few useful properties and in particular they are not computationally useful. (b) The states so defined do not correspond to physically realizable states, except under the special circumstance that the commutator of the annihilation operator (or lowering step operator) and its Hermitian adjoint is a multiple of the identity operator. Therefore, under these conditions one restricts oneself to the electromagnetic field.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ol start=&quot;2&quot; type=&quot;1&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Coherent states as minimum-uncertainty states&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[…] this generalization has several limitations. First of all, these coherent states can only be constructed for the classically integrable systems in which there exists a set of canonical coordinates and momenta such that the respective Hamiltonians can be reduced to quadrature. This condition requires a flatness condition on the Lie algebra, which reduces the commutation relations to those of the standard photon creation and annihilation operators. Secondly, the wave packets with minimum uncertainty are not unique (see Fig. 1). Different ones may have different properties. Such states may also be incomplete, or even if they are complete it is not certain that a resolution of unity of the standard form exists (Klauder and Skagerstam, 198S). Thus minimum-uncertainty states appear to have few, if any, useful properties. For example, minimum-uncertainty states do not evolve into minimum-uncertainty states when they are driven by a Hamiltonian linear in the generators in the Lie group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Revisiting this paper after a couple of years, now I would say that the group approach in which generalize coherent states (GCSs) are defined to be the orbit of a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Weight_(representation_theory)&quot;&gt;highest weight state&lt;/a&gt; does loosely generalize 1. and 2. as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Semisimple_Lie_algebra&quot;&gt;semisimple Lie algebra&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\g\)&lt;/span&gt; and its root space decomposition &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\[ \g = \overbrace{\bigoplus_{\alpha \in \Sigma^+} \g_{-\alpha}}^{\displaystyle\n^-} \oplus \h \oplus \overbrace{\bigoplus_{\alpha \in \Sigma^+} \g_{\alpha}}^{\displaystyle\n^+}, \]&lt;/span&gt; where &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\h\)&lt;/span&gt; is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cartan_subalgebra&quot;&gt;Cartan subalgebra&lt;/a&gt;, a highest weight state &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\ket{\psi}\)&lt;/span&gt; is by definition the 0-eigenvector of the nilpotent subalgebra &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\n^+\)&lt;/span&gt; of all positive roots which are analogues of the raising operators. But one might as well shuffle the labels between positive and negative roots and call elements in &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\n^+\)&lt;/span&gt; “lowering operators”. What’s important is that in a given irrep, although there is only one highest weight vector with respect to a fixed Cartan subalgebra, every state in the orbit of that vector is a highest weight vector with respect to &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; choice of a Cartan subalgebra. (In fact, a GCS in finite dimensions can be &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/0802.4008&quot;&gt;defined&lt;/a&gt; as an eigenvector of a &lt;em&gt;Borel subalgebra&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\h \oplus \n^+\)&lt;/span&gt;. This is a part of the geometric highest weight theory.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though minimum-uncertainty states don’t generalize well, &lt;em&gt;minimum variance states&lt;/em&gt; do, and the same trick of shifting Cartan subalgebras around also does the work here. Let &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\{X_j\}\)&lt;/span&gt; be an orthogonal basis of &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\g\)&lt;/span&gt;. A vector &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\psi\)&lt;/span&gt; in an irrep of highest weight &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\lambda\)&lt;/span&gt; is a GCS iff the total variance &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\[\mathrm{Var}(\psi) := \sum_j \av{X_j^2}_{\psi} - \sum_j \av{X_j}_{\psi}^2 \]&lt;/span&gt; is minimal. The first term is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Casimir_element&quot;&gt;Casimir&lt;/a&gt; eigenvalue which is fixed for a given irrep &lt;a href=&quot;#fn1&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot; id=&quot;fnref1&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. The only states that maximize the second term are, again, highest weight states with respect to some choices of Cartan subalgebras, and these are precisely the orbit of the unique highest weight state with respect to a fixed Cartan subalgebra.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The comparison here with the traditional coherent states is a bit wonky as the Heisenberg group is nilpotent and not semisimple. Zhang et al. takes the symmetry algebra of single-mode coherent states to be generated by &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\{a,a\dgg,a\dgg a,1\}\)&lt;/span&gt;, where 1 is the “scalar” in the commutator &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\([a\dgg,a] = 1\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(a\dgg a\)&lt;/span&gt; is the number operator. 1 and &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(a\dgg a\)&lt;/span&gt; each has some property of an element of a Cartan subalgebra but not all. For instance, &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(a\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(a\dgg\)&lt;/span&gt; are eigenvectors of the adjoint action of &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(a\dgg a\)&lt;/span&gt; but &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\([a\dgg,a]\)&lt;/span&gt; is not proportional to &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(a\dgg a\)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I learned these interesting characterizations of GCSs from:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/quant-ph/0206012&quot;&gt;Coherent states, entanglement, and geometric invariant theory&lt;/a&gt;, Klyachko 2002 [&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/0802.4008&quot;&gt;Extended (and corrected) version&lt;/a&gt;]
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ams.org/journals/proc/1982-084-04/S0002-9939-1982-0643758-8/S0002-9939-1982-0643758-8.pdf&quot;&gt;A system of quadrics describing the orbit of the highest weight vector&lt;/a&gt;, Lichtenstein 1982 [&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathoverflow.net/questions/49561/highest-weight-orbit-characterization-reformulated-and-extended&quot;&gt;MO&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/quant-ph/0207149&quot;&gt;Generalizations of entanglement based on coherent states and convex sets&lt;/a&gt;, Barnum, Knill, Ortiz and Viola 2003&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More GCS:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1811.08479&quot;&gt;Quantum circuit synthesis for generalized coherent states&lt;/a&gt;, Somma arXiv:1811.08479&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A highest weight state with respect to a choice of a Cartan subalgebra &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\h\)&lt;/span&gt; has a physical interpretation as the ground state of a Hamiltonian in &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\h\)&lt;/span&gt;. (That statement is manifestly false and requires two adjustments &lt;a href=&quot;#fn2&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot; id=&quot;fnref2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; but it has a nicer ring to it if you’re a physicist.) Suppose that your quantum computation starts in the ground state of a fixed &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\h_0 \subset \g\)&lt;/span&gt; and after some time you don’t know what the state is anymore but you know that it is a GCS &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\ket{\psi}\)&lt;/span&gt; under the group &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(G\)&lt;/span&gt;. This could happen, for example, if the quantum gates are limited to those in &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(G\)&lt;/span&gt;. This paper shows how to reconstruct a quantum circuit that prepares the GCS from the initial ground state by measuring observables &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\{X_j\}\)&lt;/span&gt; in &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\g\)&lt;/span&gt;. The number of measurements and the reconstruction process are efficient in the dimension of the Lie algebra.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two neat tricks: The Hamiltonian &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\[ H = - \sum_j X_j \av{X_j}_{\psi}  \]&lt;/span&gt; has &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\ket{\psi}\)&lt;/span&gt; as the ground state because the expectation value &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\[ - \av{H} =  \sum_j \av{X_j}^2 \]&lt;/span&gt; is exactly the quantity maximized only by &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\ket{\psi}\)&lt;/span&gt;. One then diagonalizes the Hamiltonian to be in &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\h_0\)&lt;/span&gt;. Any complex semisimple &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\g\)&lt;/span&gt; is a bunch of overlapping &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\sl(2,\C)\)&lt;/span&gt; subalgebras &lt;a href=&quot;#fn3&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot; id=&quot;fnref3&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and the task turns out to break up into sequentially diagonalizing each &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\sl(2,\C)\)&lt;/span&gt; subalgebra: find a rotation that brings a linear combination of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pauli_matrices&quot;&gt;Paulis&lt;/a&gt; to a pure, fixed Pauli, &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(Z\)&lt;/span&gt; for example.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://aip.scitation.org/doi/abs/10.1063/1.522663&quot;&gt;A note on coherent state representations of Lie groups&lt;/a&gt;, Onofri 1975&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(G\)&lt;/span&gt; be a real Lie group, &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(T\)&lt;/span&gt; a maximal torus, &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(K \subset G\)&lt;/span&gt; the (projective) stabilizer subgroup of a highest weight state, &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(G^{\C}\)&lt;/span&gt; the complexification of &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(G\)&lt;/span&gt;, and &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(B \subset P \subset G^{\C}\)&lt;/span&gt; the Borel and a parabolic subgroup respectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An argument for the (canonical) diffeomorphism &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(G /T \cong G^{\C} /B\)&lt;/span&gt; can be found in &lt;a href=&quot;https://projecteuclid.org/euclid.cmp/1104200934&quot;&gt;Hogreve et al. 1990&lt;/a&gt;, Section 2.3, p.472: the real span of &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\g\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\mathfrak{b}\)&lt;/span&gt; is all of &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\g^{\C}\)&lt;/span&gt;, so the &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(G\)&lt;/span&gt;-orbit is open in the &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(G^{\C}\)&lt;/span&gt; orbit (&lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(G^{\C} /B\)&lt;/span&gt;). On the other hand, the orbit is closed because of the compactness, thus they are the same. The argument extends to &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(G /K \cong G^{\C} /P\)&lt;/span&gt; by defining &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(K = P \cap G\)&lt;/span&gt;, then &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(K\)&lt;/span&gt; contains a maximal torus &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(T\)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;representation-theory&quot;&gt;Representation theory&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.math.stonybrook.edu/~aknapp/pdf-files/1-27.pdf&quot;&gt;Structure theory of semisimple Lie groups&lt;/a&gt;, Knapp 1997&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Algebraic groups&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://hkumath.hku.hk/~imr/records0001/borel.pdf&quot;&gt;Lie Groups and Linear Algebraic Groups I. Complex and Real Groups&lt;/a&gt;, Borel&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jmilne.org/math/CourseNotes/aag.pdf&quot;&gt;Algebraic Groups and Arithmetic Groups&lt;/a&gt;, Milne 2005&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www-fourier.ujf-grenoble.fr/~mbrion/notes_luminy.pdf&quot;&gt;Introduction to actions of algebraic groups&lt;/a&gt;, Brion 2009&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.math.columbia.edu/~makisumi/articles/reductivegroups.pdf&quot;&gt;Structure theory of reductive groups through examples&lt;/a&gt;, Makisumi 2011&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://math.stackexchange.com/a/76153&quot;&gt;Peter-Weyl for compact Lie groups vs algebraic groups&lt;/a&gt;, MSE (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Lie-Groups-Invariants-Representations-Universitext/dp/0387260404&quot;&gt;Procesi&lt;/a&gt;, for example, has both verions: compare Chapter 7, p. 180 and the Peter-Weyl theorem in Chapter 8, p. 213)
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Distribution_on_a_linear_algebraic_group&quot;&gt;Distributions on a linear algebraic group&lt;/a&gt;, Wikipedia&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Symmetric spaces and multiplicities&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Foundations of Differential Geometry&lt;/em&gt;, Vol. 2, Kobayashi and Nomizu 1963&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Perspectives on Invariant Theory: Schur Duality, Multiplicity-Free Actions and Beyond in &lt;em&gt;The Schur Lectures&lt;/em&gt;, Howe 1992&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ims.nus.edu.sg/Programs/liegroups/files/mfalectures-chal-gail.pdf&quot;&gt;Notes on multiplicity-free actions&lt;/a&gt;, Benson and Ratcliff&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ams.org/journals/ert/2003-007-18/S1088-4165-03-00150-X/S1088-4165-03-00150-X.pdf&quot;&gt;Multiplicity-free products and restriction of Weyl characters&lt;/a&gt;, Stembridge 2003&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0021869384711458&quot;&gt;On spherical double cones&lt;/a&gt;, Littelmann 1994&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Cartan-Helgason theorem [&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zonal_spherical_function#Cartan%E2%80%93Helgason_theore&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;]
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Harmonic Analysis on Semi-Simple Lie Groups I&lt;/em&gt;, Warner 1972&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Groups and Geometric Analysis&lt;/em&gt;, Helgason 1984 (p. 535)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Symmetry, Representations, and Invariants&lt;/em&gt;, Goodman and Wallach 2009 (Chapter 12)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;media&quot;&gt;Media&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Added to the list of great scientists we’ve lost in 2018 are &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/sapinker/status/1079436841017851906&quot;&gt;Judith Rich Harris&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;em&gt;Nurture Assumption&lt;/em&gt; fame and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/local/obituaries/roy-glauber-nobel-winning-physicist-who-applied-quantum-mechanics-to-optics-dies-at-93/2018/12/30/b7e4e05e-0b24-11e9-a3f0-71c95106d96a_story.html&quot;&gt;Roy Glauber&lt;/a&gt;. Glauber and E.C.G. Sudarshan (who also passed away earlier in 2018), are both monumental figures that helped define the field of quantum optics that we know today.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Apparently living in an area with 22 &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\mu g/m^3\)&lt;/span&gt; of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Particulates&quot;&gt;PM2.5&lt;/a&gt; is &lt;a href=&quot;http://berkeleyearth.org/air-pollution-and-cigarette-equivalence/&quot;&gt;equivalent to smoking a cigarette per day&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Average individual consumption is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/KevinSimler/status/1077196864494067712&quot;&gt;better proxy for wealth&lt;/a&gt; than GDP.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://strikemag.org/bullshit-jobs/&quot;&gt;Bullshit Jobs&lt;/a&gt;, Graeber 2013 [&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/slatestarcodex/comments/62llb0/on_the_phenomenon_of_bullshit_jobs/&quot;&gt;SSC subreddit&lt;/a&gt;]
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/news/2018/jan/19/post-work-the-radical-idea-of-a-world-without-jobs&quot;&gt;Post-Work&lt;/a&gt;, Guardian&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2130471/&quot;&gt;Fried rice syndrome&lt;/a&gt; [&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bacillus_cereus&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bmj.com/content/363/bmj.k5094&quot;&gt;Parachute use to prevent death and major trauma when jumping from aircraft: randomized controlled trial&lt;/a&gt;, Yeh &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt; 2018 (The now classic &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bmj.com/content/327/7429/1459&quot;&gt;2003 paper&lt;/a&gt; by Smith and Pell was a literature review. Here they actually did the experiment.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bbc.com/future/story/20190109-the-perils-of-short-termism-civilisations-greatest-threat&quot;&gt;The perils of short-termism: Civilization’s greatest threat&lt;/a&gt;, BBC&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To paraphrase the investor Esther Dyson: in politics the dominant time frame is a term of office, in fashion and culture it’s a season, for corporations it’s a quarter, on the internet it’s minutes, and on the financial markets mere milliseconds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When is it acceptable to offset a bad deed by a good deed? A simple rule: &lt;a href=&quot;http://slatestarcodex.com/2017/08/28/contra-askell-on-moral-offsets/&quot;&gt;you can offset axiology, but not morality&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/science/archive/2018/11/diminishing-returns-science/575665/&quot;&gt;Science is getting less bang for its buck&lt;/a&gt;, Collison and Nielsen, Atlantic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/XYYyzgyuRH5rFN64K/what-makes-people-intellectually-active&quot;&gt;What makes people intellectually active?&lt;/a&gt;, LW
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;William Shockley &lt;a href=&quot;https://dynamicecology.wordpress.com/2014/01/23/william-shockley-on-what-makes-a-person-write-a-lot-of-papers-and-the-superstar-researcher-system/&quot;&gt;observed&lt;/a&gt; that the distribution of productivity at Bell labs was &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Log-normal_distribution&quot;&gt;log-normal&lt;/a&gt;, which could arise from a product of i.i.d. distributions of several different abilities e.g. the ability to recognize a good problem, solve it, write about it, persevere in the battle with reviewers, write a grant proposal, bring in money etc. (As a side note, the median of the number of citations is apparently zero!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Physics Forums has a nice Insight article on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.physicsforums.com/insights/groups-and-geometry/&quot;&gt;Klein geometries&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Differential Geometry: Cartan’s Generalization of Klein’s Erlangen program&lt;/em&gt;, Sharpe 1997 (More examples of planar Klein’s geometries. There are 23 families of two-dimensional Klein’s geometries)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Desargues%27s_theorem&quot;&gt;Desargues’ theorem&lt;/a&gt; in projective geometry is quoted in several treatises of perspective drawing according to this &lt;a href=&quot;https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01015873&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cube20.org/&quot;&gt;God’s Number is 20&lt;/a&gt;: the longest shortest sequence to solve a Rubik’s cube is 20 moves in the half-turn metric (any non-trivial turn of a face counts as one move).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anime&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yhGjCzxJV3E&quot;&gt;Guilty Gear Xrd’s Art Style : The X Factor Between 2D and 3D&lt;/a&gt;, Junya C. Motomura, Lead character modeler&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Team Red of Arc System Works was the only one that got anime-like cel-shading right. (They were thus given the job to handle &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dragon_Ball_FighterZ&quot;&gt;Dragon Ball FighterZ&lt;/a&gt; and now &lt;a href=&quot;(https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZQQo9vSj1_A)&quot;&gt;Granblue Fantasy Versus&lt;/a&gt;). Each character has its own fixed light source and the team manually adjusts the normal vector and the cel-shading threshold of each major polygon face (&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/yhGjCzxJV3E?t=970&quot;&gt;16:10&lt;/a&gt;) to make sure that every close-up frame looks good.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Good &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nicovideo.jp/watch/sm34393460&quot;&gt;Touhou anime parody&lt;/a&gt; still exists in 2019. (Onegai! Cinderella, The Idolm@ster Cinderella Girls)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://foreignpolicy.com/2019/01/23/super-patriotic-anime-youth-wars-china-japan-pop-culture/&quot;&gt;China’s responses to Japanese anime invasion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;physicsquantum&quot;&gt;Physics/quantum&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trump signs the $1.2 billion &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.technologyreview.com/the-download/612679/president-trump-has-signed-a-12-billon-law-to-boost-us-quantum-tech/&quot;&gt;National Quantum Initiative Act&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://cognitivemedium.com/qc-a-science&quot;&gt;In what sense is quantum computing a science?&lt;/a&gt;, Nielsen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A sensible &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hpcwire.com/2019/01/09/the-case-against-the-case-against-quantum-computing/&quot;&gt;rebuttal&lt;/a&gt; to what I think is a fundamentally misguided piece, &lt;a href=&quot;https://spectrum.ieee.org/computing/hardware/the-case-against-quantum-computing&quot;&gt;The Case Against Quantum Computing&lt;/a&gt; that appeared in IEEE Spectrum last November.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Boaz Barak’s blog, &lt;a href=&quot;https://windowsontheory.org&quot;&gt;Windows on Theory&lt;/a&gt;, is having a series of guest blog posts on connections between computer science and physics. The topics range from statistical-physics-inspired algorithms to quantum information and black hole information paradox.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/has-ligo-seen-galaxy-warped-gravitational-waves/&quot;&gt;George Smoot thinks&lt;/a&gt; that the region of the universe around us lacks “low-metallica” stars, giant stars that can collapse and give rise to &amp;gt;20 solar-mass black holes that LIGO and Virgo have been detecting, and so surmises that the events we have seen took place “much farther away—on the order of 10 billion light-years distant—magnified and made visible through gravitational lensing”.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;meditation&quot;&gt;Meditation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/1745691617709589&quot;&gt;Mind the Hype: A Critical Evaluation and Prescriptive Agenda for Research on Mindfulness and Meditation&lt;/a&gt;, Van Dam et al. 2017&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/wheres-the-proof-that-mindfulness-meditation-works1/&quot;&gt;Where’s the Proof That Mindfulness Meditation Works?&lt;/a&gt;, SA [&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/skeptic/comments/76az0f/wheres_the_proof_that_mindfulness_meditation_works/dod3rpo/&quot;&gt;reddit comment&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Altered-Traits-Science-Reveals-Meditation/dp/0399184384&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Altered traits: science reveals how meditation changes your mind, brain, and body&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Goleman and Davidson 2017 [&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.stitcher.com/podcast/abc-news/10-happier/e/51407909&quot;&gt;Dan Harris’ podcast&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/M4w2rdYgCKctbADMn/sequence-introduction-non-agent-and-multiagent-models-of&quot;&gt;Sequence introduction: non-agent and multiagent models of mind&lt;/a&gt;, Sotala, LW
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lesswrong.com/s/ZbmRyDN8TCpBTZSip/p/x4n4jcoDP7xh5LWLq&quot;&gt;Book Summary: &lt;em&gt;Consciousness and the Brain&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lesswrong.com/s/ZbmRyDN8TCpBTZSip/p/5gfqG3Xcopscta3st&quot;&gt;Building up to an Internal Family Systems model&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thomas Metzinger formalizes &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.blogs.uni-mainz.de/fb05philosophie/files/2013/04/Metzinger_suffering_penultimate.pdf&quot;&gt;necessary conditions for suffering&lt;/a&gt;: 1. conscious experience 2. self-model 3. negative values in the self-model 4. identification with the self-model. Buddhism’s “no self” strives to eliminate 2 (and consequently 3 and 4).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;musics&quot;&gt;Musics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-tKVN2mAKRI&quot;&gt;Uchiage hanabi&lt;/a&gt;, DAOKO X Yonezu Kenshi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Fj9Y9TGQn38&quot;&gt;Shadowgraph&lt;/a&gt;, Myth &amp;amp; Roid {Boogiepop wa warawanai 2019} [OP]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=301-O2GbXuE&quot;&gt;99.9&lt;/a&gt;, MOB CHOIR feat. sajou no hana {Mob Psycho 100 II} [OP]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-SjrlKsibqM&quot;&gt;Sayonara Gokko&lt;/a&gt;, amazarashi {Dororo 2019} [ED]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://streamable.com/423z4&quot;&gt;Love Dramatic feat. Rikka Ihara&lt;/a&gt;, Masayuki Suzuki {Kaguya-sama wa kokurasetai} [OP]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;touhou&quot;&gt;Touhou&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=l_G3i92kX-Q&quot;&gt;弦魔術狂想曲&lt;/a&gt; (Mary the Magician), FAR EAST OF EAST -XVI- (C94), TatshMusicCircle&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KsASO-I5ki0&quot;&gt;Never Ending Night&lt;/a&gt; (Spring Lane ~ Colorful Path), &lt;a href=&quot;https://vgmdb.net/album/21282&quot;&gt;東方零響奇譚 ~ Sophisticated Insanity&lt;/a&gt; (C79), Zero Symphonic Battalion (Hiroki Kikuta, Jillian Aversa)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=V2JuT1tiKQs&quot;&gt;最終制御室～Final control room～&lt;/a&gt; (Last Remote), &lt;a href=&quot;https://vgmdb.net/album/35142&quot;&gt;東方幻霊殿&lt;/a&gt; (C82), Ryuuha Mikakutei&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9MiNHqR6yuw&quot;&gt;空へと沈む鬼と針の城&lt;/a&gt; (The Shining Needle Castle Sinking in the Air), &lt;a href=&quot;https://vgmdb.net/album/43555&quot;&gt;逆弾奏結界 反逆諧謔曲 Reversal Scherzo&lt;/a&gt; (C85), dBu&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ChEdrrrqn5s&quot;&gt;魔界地方遊戯ソリテェア&lt;/a&gt; (Makai Provincial City Esoteria), &lt;a href=&quot;https://vgmdb.net/album/17064&quot;&gt;Lotus&lt;/a&gt; (C77), Sound.AVE&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=d8doAEtfcnc&quot;&gt;Sealed Sword &amp;amp; Alice in Wonderland&lt;/a&gt; (The Grimoire of Alice &amp;amp; Alice in Wonderland), &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.touhouwiki.net/wiki/Ancient_Treasures&quot;&gt;Ancient Treasures&lt;/a&gt; (C79), Oriens&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;section class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn1&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Casimir eigenvalue is &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\av{\lambda,\lambda + 2\delta}\)&lt;/span&gt;, generalizing the &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(j(j+1)\)&lt;/span&gt; of the squared angular momentum, where &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\delta = \frac{1}{2}\sum_{\alpha \in \Sigma_+} \alpha\)&lt;/span&gt; is the ubiquitous half-sum of positive roots (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Lie-Groups-Introduction-Anthony-Knapp/dp/0817642595&quot;&gt;Knapp&lt;/a&gt;, Proposition 5.28, p.295). For highest weight states, &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\sum_j \av{X_j}^2 = \av{\lambda,\lambda}\)&lt;/span&gt;, making the variance &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\av{\lambda,2\delta}\)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn2&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;One we already discussed is that the ground state would be the lowest weight state but we can make it the highest weight state by a trivial relabeling. The other is that the set of Hermitian matrices are not closed under the commutator bracket so Hamiltonians don’t form a Lie algebra. Rather it is &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(i\)&lt;/span&gt; times the Hamiltonians that are in &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\h\)&lt;/span&gt;. These exponentiate directly into group elements.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref2&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn3&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;For each &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\alpha\)&lt;/span&gt;, the Lie algebra generated by &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\{ E_{\pm \alpha}, H \}\)&lt;/span&gt;, where &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(E_{\pm \alpha} \in \g_{\pm \alpha}\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(H \propto [E_{\alpha},E_{-\alpha}] \in h\)&lt;/span&gt; is isomorphic to the &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\sl(2,\C)\)&lt;/span&gt; Lie algebra. Note that &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\sl(2,\C)\)&lt;/span&gt; is what physicists call “&lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\mathfrak{su}(2)\)&lt;/span&gt;” but it is actually the complexification of the &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; Lie algebra &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\mathfrak{su}(2)\)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref3&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>อัลกอริธึมของชอร์ (ยังเขียนไม่เสร็จ)</title>
   <link href="/shor.html"/>
   <updated>2018-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>h/shor</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/posts/2018/summer-wars-shor.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Kenji, meets Shor. Shor, meets Kenji.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;อัลกอริธึมแยกตัวประกอบเป็นแอปพลิเคชันของคอมพิวเตอร์ควอนตัมที่สำคัญที่สุดหรือเปล่า? ส่วนตัวผมคิดว่าการจำลองระบบควอนตัมจะส่งผลกระทบที่ยิ่งใหญ่กว่าต่อวิทยาศาสตร์และสังคม แต่การทำลายระบบความปลอดภัย RSA เป็นเรื่องที่มักจะถูกถามบ่อยที่สุดก็เลยอยากจะเขียนเอาไว้หน่อย (มี&lt;a href=&quot;https://khunpanya.wordpress.com/2016/07/31/shors-algorithm/&quot;&gt;บล็อก&lt;/a&gt;ของคุณปัญญาอีกบล็อกที่เขียนเรื่องอัลกอริธึมนี้)&lt;/p&gt;
ก่อนอื่นเลย อัลกอริธึมแยกตัวประกอบของชอร์เป็นอัลกอริธึมหาคาบ (period finding) ของฟังก์ชันประเภทหนึ่ง ดังนั้นเราต้องมาเข้าใจกันก่อนว่าปัญหาการทำลายระบบ RSA และการแยกตัวประกอบลดรูปไปเป็นการหาคาบได้อย่างไร ซึ่งความเข้าใจส่วนนี้ไม่เกี่ยวกับควอนตัมเลย เป็นทฤษฎีจำนวนล้วนๆ ตอนก่อนจะมาเรียนฟิสิกส์ผมเคยบอกเพื่อนภาคคณิตศาสตร์ว่าชีวิตนี้จะไม่แตะทฤษฎีจำนวนอีกแล้วแต่การคำนวณเชิงควอนตัมทำให้ผมต้องผิดคำพูด (แต่เดี๋ยวก็จะเห็นว่ามันเป็นทฤษฎีกรุ๊ปเสียส่วนใหญ่) ในส่วนแรกของโพสท์นี้เราจะลดรูปปัญหาทีละขั้นๆดังนี้
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
ทำลายระบบ RSA ≤ หา totient function ≤ แยกตัวประกอบ ≤ หารากที่สองที่ไม่ชัดของ 1 ≤ หาคาบ
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;โดย A ≤ B หมายความคร่าวๆว่าถ้าแก้ B ได้ก็แก้ A ได้ใน polynomial time&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;ทำลายระบบ-rsa-ดวยการแยกตวประกอบ&quot;&gt;ทำลายระบบ RSA ด้วยการแยกตัวประกอบ&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ใน&lt;a href=&quot;https://ninnat.github.io/quantum-algorithms.html&quot;&gt;โพสท์ที่แล้ว&lt;/a&gt;ผมอธิบายการทำงานของรหัส RSA ไว้อย่างคร่าวๆ โดยไม่ใช้สมการ แต่ในโพสท์นี้ไม่ใช้ไม่ได้แล้ว ให้ &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(m\)&lt;/span&gt; เป็นข้อความ (message), &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(e\)&lt;/span&gt; เป็นกุญแจเข้ารหัสลับ (encryption key), และ &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(d\)&lt;/span&gt; เป็นกุญแจถอดรหัส (decryption key) ระบบ RSA เข้ารหัสด้วยการเลือกจำนวนเต็ม &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(N\)&lt;/span&gt; และคำนวณ &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(m\)&lt;/span&gt; ยกกำลัง &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(e\)&lt;/span&gt; ในเลขคณิตนาฬิกา &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\[ f(m) \equiv m^e \mod N \]&lt;/span&gt; ส่วนการถอดรหัสทำโดยยกกำลังอีกครั้งจนได้ข้อความเดิมกลับมา &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\[ (m^e)^d = m^{ed} \equiv m \mod N \]&lt;/span&gt; ในการ&lt;a href=&quot;https://ninnat.github.io/quantum-algorithms.html&quot;&gt;เข้ารหัสด้วยกุญแจสาธารณะ&lt;/a&gt; (public key cryptography) ทุกๆคนมีสิทธิ์ที่จะรู้ &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(e\)&lt;/span&gt; และ &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(N\)&lt;/span&gt; แต่ผู้รับสาส์นเท่านั้นที่จะมีกุญแจถอดรหัส &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(d\)&lt;/span&gt; เตรียมอยู่แล้ว ดังนั้นคำถามของนักแฮกก็คือเราจะคำนวณ &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(d\)&lt;/span&gt; จาก &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(e\)&lt;/span&gt; และ &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(N\)&lt;/span&gt; ได้อย่างไร? &lt;a href=&quot;#fn1&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot; id=&quot;fnref1&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ปรากฏว่าถ้าเราแยกตัวประกอบได้ เราก็หาค่า &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(M\)&lt;/span&gt; ที่ทำให้ &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\[ ed \equiv 1 \mod M \]&lt;/span&gt; ได้ ยกตัวอย่างเช่น เมื่อ &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(N\)&lt;/span&gt; เป็นผลคูณของจำนวนเฉพาะแค่สองจำนวน &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(N=pq\)&lt;/span&gt; ค่าของ &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(M\)&lt;/span&gt; คือ &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\((p-1)(q-1)\)&lt;/span&gt; จากนั้นเราสามารถหาอินเวอร์สการคูณของ &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(e\)&lt;/span&gt; ใน &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\text{mod}\,M\)&lt;/span&gt; ด้วย&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Extended_Euclidean_algorithm#Computing_multiplicative_inverses_in_modular_structures&quot;&gt;อัลกอริธึมของยูคลิด&lt;/a&gt; ได้กุญแจถอดรหัส &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(d\)&lt;/span&gt; ออกมา ปัญหาการทำลายระบบ RSA จึงลดรูปเป็นปัญหาการแยกตัวประกอบได้ &lt;a href=&quot;#fn2&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot; id=&quot;fnref2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ถ้าต้องการหาค่า &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(M\)&lt;/span&gt; โดยทั่วไป มันคือ &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Euler%27s_totient_function&quot;&gt;totient function&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\varphi(N)\)&lt;/span&gt; ของออยเลอร์ซึ่งผมแอบซ่อนรายละเอียดเอาไว้ด้านล่าง สามารถคลิกลูกศรเพื่อเปิดดูได้&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;strong&gt;การหาค่าของ &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(M\)&lt;/span&gt;: &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(N\)&lt;/span&gt; เป็นจำนวนเฉพาะ&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

การคำนวณ totient function เป็น generalization ของ&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fermat%27s_little_theorem&quot;&gt;ทฤษฎีบทน้อยๆของแฟร์มา&lt;/a&gt; (Fermat’s little theorem): เมื่อ &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(p\)&lt;/span&gt; เป็นจำนวนเฉพาะและ &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(a\)&lt;/span&gt; กับ &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(p\)&lt;/span&gt; เป็น coprime (ห.ร.ม.=1) &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\[ a^{p-1} \equiv 1 \mod p \]&lt;/span&gt; ทฤษฎีบทนี้&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Proofs_of_Fermat%27s_little_theorem&quot;&gt;พิสูจน์&lt;/a&gt; ได้ด้วยทฤษฎีกรุ๊ป จำนวนใน &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\mathbb{Z}_p\)&lt;/span&gt; ที่มีอินเวอร์การคูณประกอบกันเป็น cyclic group &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\mathbb{Z}_p^*\)&lt;/span&gt; ซึ่งมีขนาด &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(p-1\)&lt;/span&gt; (เพราะจำนวนทุกจำนวนที่เป็น coprime กับ &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(p\)&lt;/span&gt; เป็น generators ของกรุ๊ปหมด เหลือแค่ &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(p\)&lt;/span&gt; ตัวเดียวที่ไม่มีอินเวิร์ส) &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(a^{p-1}\)&lt;/span&gt; จึงเท่ากับ 1 mod &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(p\)&lt;/span&gt; ด้วย&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lagrange%27s_theorem_(group_theory)&quot;&gt;ทฤษฎีบทของลากรานจ์&lt;/a&gt; เพราะกรุ๊ปที่ generated โดย &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(a\)&lt;/span&gt; เป็นซับกรุ๊ป (subgroup) ของ &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\mathbb{Z}_p^*\)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/details&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;strong&gt;การหาค่าของ &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(M\)&lt;/span&gt;: &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(N\)&lt;/span&gt; เป็นกำลังของจำนวนเฉพาะ&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

เมื่อ &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(N\)&lt;/span&gt; เป็นกำลังของจำนวนเฉพาะ (prime power) &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(N = p^r\)&lt;/span&gt;, จำนวนที่ไม่เป็น coprime กับ &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(p^r\)&lt;/span&gt; ใน &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\mathbb{Z}_{p^r}\)&lt;/span&gt; และไม่มากกว่า &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(p^r\)&lt;/span&gt; คือ &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(p,2p,\cdots,p^{r-1}p\)&lt;/span&gt; ซึ่งมี &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(p^{r-1}\)&lt;/span&gt; จำนวน ดังนั้น &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\varphi(N) = p^r - p^{r-1}\)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/details&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;strong&gt;การหาค่าของ &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(M\)&lt;/span&gt;: &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(N\)&lt;/span&gt; ทั่วไป&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

เมื่อ &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(N\)&lt;/span&gt; เป็นผลคูณของกำลังของจำนวนเฉพาะ &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(N = p_1^{r_1} p_2^{r_2}\)&lt;/span&gt; เราสามารถ&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Euler%27s_totient_function#Computing_Euler%27s_totient_function&quot;&gt;พิสูจน์&lt;/a&gt;ได้ว่า totient function เป็นผลคูณ &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\varphi(p_1^{r_1}) \varphi(p_2^{r_2})\)&lt;/span&gt; หรือ &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\[ \varphi(p_1^{r_1}p_2^{r_2} \cdots p_k^{r_k}) = (p_1^{r_1}-p_1^{r_1-1}) (p_2^{r_2}-p_2^{r_2-1}) \cdots (p_k^{r_k}-p_k^{r_k-1}) \]&lt;/span&gt; นั่นเอง ทำให้ได้ว่า &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\[ \varphi(N) = (p-1)(q-1) \]&lt;/span&gt; เมื่อ &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(N\)&lt;/span&gt; เป็นผลคูณของจำนวนเฉพาะสองจำนวน
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/details&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;การที่ RSA รักษาความปลอดภัยได้ก็เพราะไม่มีใครมีอัลกอริธึมคลาสสิคัลที่แยกตัวประกอบได้อย่างรวดเร็ว วิธีหนึ่งในการหาตัวประกอบของ &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(N\)&lt;/span&gt; คือไล่หาร &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(N\)&lt;/span&gt; ด้วยจำนวนเล็กๆไปเรื่อยๆจนกว่าจะเจอตัวหาร ซึ่งอาจจะต้องหารไปถึง &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\sqrt{N}\)&lt;/span&gt; ตัว ทำไมนี่ไม่ใช่อัลกอริธึม polynomial-time ล่ะ? เหตุผลก็คือเราต้องการแค่ &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\log N\)&lt;/span&gt; บิตในการบันทึกจำนวนเต็ม &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(N\)&lt;/span&gt; ขนาดของอินพุตจึงไม่ใช่ &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(N\)&lt;/span&gt; แต่เป็น &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(n=\log N\)&lt;/span&gt; ต่างหาก อัลกอริธึมไล่หารโง่ๆจึงใช้เวลา &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(2^{n/2}\)&lt;/span&gt; อัลกอริธึม Number Field Sieve ที่ดีสุด ก็&lt;a href=&quot;http://math.mit.edu/~cohn/Thoughts/factoring.html&quot;&gt;ใช้เวลา&lt;/a&gt;ประมาณ &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(2^{n^{1/3}}\)&lt;/span&gt; ยังคงเป็นทวีคูณ (exponential) ในขนาดของอินพุต&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;แยกตวประกอบดวยการหาคาบ&quot;&gt;แยกตัวประกอบด้วยการหาคาบ&lt;/h2&gt;
สิ่งที่นักวิทยาศาสตร์คอมพิวเตอร์รู้มาก่อนชอร์แล้วก็คือถ้าเราสุ่มเอาจำนวน &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(a\)&lt;/span&gt; มาหาคาบใน &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\text{mod}\,N\)&lt;/span&gt; เยอะๆ เราก็จะหาตัวประกอบของ &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(N\)&lt;/span&gt; ได้ &lt;a href=&quot;#fn3&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot; id=&quot;fnref3&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; คาบของ &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(a\)&lt;/span&gt; คือคาบของฟังก์ชันยกกำลัง &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(a^x\,\,\text{mod}\,N\)&lt;/span&gt; (modular exponentiation) ยกตัวอย่างเช่นถ้าเราจับ &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(a=2\)&lt;/span&gt; ยกกำลังไปเรื่อยๆใน &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\text{mod}\,21\)&lt;/span&gt; ค่ามันก็จะวนซ้ำทุกๆ 6 ตัว
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;header&quot;&gt;
&lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;x&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;1&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;2&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;3&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;4&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;5&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;6&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;7&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;8&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;9&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;10&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;11&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;odd&quot;&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(2^x\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;16&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;16&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;เราเรียกค่านี้ว่าคาบของ &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(a\)&lt;/span&gt; คือจำนวน &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(r\)&lt;/span&gt; ที่น้อยที่สุดที่ &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\[a^r \equiv 1 \mod N\]&lt;/span&gt; หาก &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(N\)&lt;/span&gt; มี &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(k\)&lt;/span&gt; ตัวประกอบ โอกาสที่จะสุ่มได้ &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(a\)&lt;/span&gt; ที่ให้ตัวประกอบเมื่อนำมาหาคาบคือ &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(1-1/2^{k-1}\)&lt;/span&gt; คือยังไงก็มีโอกาสไม่น้อยไปกว่าครึ่ง&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;strong&gt;รากที่สองที่ไม่ชัดของ 1 ให้ตัวประกอบ&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

ไอเดียก็คือถ้า &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(r\)&lt;/span&gt; หารด้วย 2 ลงตัว &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(a^{r/2}\)&lt;/span&gt; ก็จะเป็นรากที่สองของ 1 ใน &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\text{mod}\,N\)&lt;/span&gt; จากนั้นก็ใช้ไอเดียจาก&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Miller%E2%80%93Rabin_primality_test&quot;&gt;การทดสอบจำนวนเฉพาะของมิลเลอร์และราบิน&lt;/a&gt; (Miller-Rabin primality testing): รากที่สองของ 1 &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\[ b^2 \equiv 1 \mod N \]&lt;/span&gt; มีแน่ๆอยู่แล้วสองตัวคือ 1 และ &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(-1 \equiv N-1\,\,\text{mod}\,N\)&lt;/span&gt; เรียกว่ารากที่สองที่ชัด (trivial) แต่ถ้าเมื่อไรมีรากที่สองมากไปกว่านี้ (nontrivial square root) &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(N\)&lt;/span&gt; จะต้องเป็นจำนวนประกอบเพราะหาก &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(b \not\equiv \pm 1\,\,\text{mod}\,N\)&lt;/span&gt; และ &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\[ b^2 -1 = (b+1)(b-1) \equiv 0 \mod N \]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(N\)&lt;/span&gt; จะต้องหาร &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\((b+1)(b-1)\)&lt;/span&gt; ลงตัว แต่ &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(N\)&lt;/span&gt; หาร &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(b+1\)&lt;/span&gt; หรือ &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(b-1\)&lt;/span&gt; โดดๆไม่ลงตัว (เพราะ &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(b \pm 1 \not\equiv 0\,\,\text{mod}\,N\)&lt;/span&gt;) &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(N\)&lt;/span&gt; จึงต้องเป็นผลคูณของตัวประกอบที่แบ่งไปหาร &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(b+1\)&lt;/span&gt; กับ &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(b-1\)&lt;/span&gt; แยกกัน ด้วยเหตุนี้ ห.ร.ม.ของ &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(b \pm 1\)&lt;/span&gt; และ &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(N\)&lt;/span&gt; จึงเป็นตัวประกอบของ &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(N\)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/details&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ความน่าจะเป็นที่ &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(a\)&lt;/span&gt; จะให้รากที่สองที่ไม่ชัดของ 1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

ยังไม่ได้เขียน
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/details&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;การแปลงฟเรยร&quot;&gt;การแปลงฟูเรียร์&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;หาคาบดวยอลกอรธมควอนตม&quot;&gt;หาคาบด้วยอัลกอริธึมควอนตัม&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;ขอควรระวงในการรนอลกอรธม&quot;&gt;ข้อควรระวังในการรันอัลกอริธึม&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Compiled Shor’s algorithm”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;ความซบซอนของการแยกตวประกอบ&quot;&gt;ความซับซ้อนของการแยกตัวประกอบ&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Factoring อยู่ใน NP ∩ coNP เชื่อว่าไม่ NP-complete มิฉะนั้น PH จะยุบมาถึงระดับที่หนึ่ง (NP=coNP=PH)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn1&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;ถ้าไม่คิดอะไร เราอาจจะนึกว่า &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(ed \equiv 1\,\,\text{mod}\,N\)&lt;/span&gt; คือคำตอบ แต่ &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(a^{b\,\,\text{mod}\,N} \not\equiv a^b\,\,\text{mod}\,N\)&lt;/span&gt; เช่น &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(2^5 \equiv 2^{1\,\,\text{mod}\,4}\)&lt;/span&gt; แต่ &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(2^5 = 32 \equiv 0\,\,\text{mod}\,4\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn2&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;จริงๆแล้วการแยกตัวประกอบก็ลดรูปเป็นปัญหาการทำลายระบบ RSA ได้ด้วย randomized polynomial-time algorithm จึงกล่าวได้ว่าทั้งสองปัญหาเป็นปัญหาเดียวกัน (Cristopher Moore และ Stephan Mertens, &lt;em&gt;The Nature of Computation&lt;/em&gt; หน้า 895)&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref2&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn3&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;หรือถ้าเช็คว่า &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(a\)&lt;/span&gt; เป็นจำนวนเฉพาะ (ซึ่งทำได้ใน &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Primality_test&quot;&gt;polynomial time&lt;/a&gt;) และโชคดี ห.ร.ม. ของ &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(a\)&lt;/span&gt; กับ &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(N\)&lt;/span&gt; ไม่ใช่ 1 ก็จบ ห.ร.ม.นั่นแหละคือตัวประกอบ&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref3&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>ขั้นคิดคำนวณแบบควอนตัม</title>
   <link href="/quantum-algorithms.html"/>
   <updated>2017-08-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>h/quantum-algorithms</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;เมื่อหนึ่งปีเต็มที่แล้วถูกชักชวนจากจิรวัฒน์ ตั้งปณิธานนท์ (Center for Quantum Technologies, สิงคโปร์) ให้ไปช่วยเขียนหนังสือให้ความรู้เกี่ยวกับคอมพิวเตอร์เชิงควอนตัม ด้วยความช่วยเหลือตรวจแก้จากบรรณาธิการและผู้ร่วมชะตากรรมเขียนคนอื่นๆทำให้สำเร็จออกมาเป็นหนังสือ(ฟรี) &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ebooks.in.th/ebook/45594/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;รูป รส กลิ่น เสียง สัมผัส ไอทีควอนตัม (๓): “คอมพิวเตอร์เชิงควอนตัม”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; จนได้ แต่ส่วนที่มีคณิตศาสตร์ที่เกินกว่าการนับเลขถูกตัดออกหมดก็เลยอยากจะลงต้นฉบับที่มีคณิตศาสตร์ไว้ ณ ที่นี้เพื่อความเข้าใจคอมพิวเตอร์เชิงควอนตัมที่แม่นยำและลึกซึ้งขึ้นครับ (ขอขอบคุณปัณฑิตา ผลิตผลการพิมพ์ ที่อ่านและวิจารณ์ดราฟท์แรกอย่างละเอียดจนกลายมาเป็นต้นฉบับนี้ได้ แต่ข้อผิดพลาดใดๆหรือภาษาที่ไม่สละสลวยเป็นความรับผิดชอบของผมเอง)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;อลกอรธมนนสำคญไฉน&quot;&gt;อัลกอริธึมนั้นสำคัญไฉน&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/posts/08-2017/koenigsberg-merian-erben_1652.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width: 628px;&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;นี่คือหน้าตาของเมืองเคอนิกสแบร์ก (Königsberg) ในศตวรรษที่ 18 ที่แม่น้ำ Pregel ไหลผ่านตัดแยกตัวเมืองเป็นสี่ผืนดินที่เชื่อมกันด้วยสะพานเจ็ดสะพาน (ก่อนจะเหลือแค่ห้าจากการทิ้งระเบิดสมัยสงครามโลกครั้งที่สอง) ชาวเมืองเคอนิกสแบร์กมักจะใช้เวลาบ่ายวันอาทิตย์เดินชมเมืองอันสวยงามของพวกเขา จนมีคนนึกสนุกตั้งปัญหาขึ้นมาว่าเป็นไปได้ไหมที่จะเดินข้ามสะพานครบทั้งเจ็ดสะพานโดยไม่ข้ามสะพานใดสะพานหนึ่งมากกว่าหนึ่งครั้ง?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;อีกปัญหาที่มีความคล้ายกันมากมาจากเกมที่วิลเลียม โรวัน แฮมิลตัน (William Rowan Hamilton) ชาวไอริชคิดขึ้นในปี 1857 ชื่อว่าเกมไอโคเซียน (Icosian) เป้าหมายของเกมคือการหาเส้นทางเดินบนขอบ (ที่เป็นเส้นหนึ่งมิติ ไม่ใช่หน้า) ของรูปเหลี่ยม 12 หน้า (dodecahedron) ที่ผ่านทุกมุมแต่ไม่ผ่านมุมใดมุมหนึ่งมากกว่าหนึ่งครั้ง&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/posts/08-2017/dodecahedron.png&quot; style=&quot;width: 300px;&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ในทางคณิตศาสตร์แล้ว ทั้งสองปัญหาคือปัญหาเกี่ยวกับการเดินบนเน็ตเวิร์คซึ่งเป็นโครงสร้างที่ประกอบด้วยเส้นเชื่อม (edge) และโหนด (หรือจุดยอด vertex) เกมไอโคเซียนถามหาเส้นทางเดินบนเน็ตเวิร์คที่ผ่านทุกๆโหนดแต่ไม่ผ่านโหนดใดโหนดหนึ่งมากกว่าหนึ่งครั้ง ในขณะที่ปัญหาสะพานทั้งเจ็ดของเคอนิกสแบร์กถามหาเส้นทางเดินบนเน็ตเวิร์คที่ผ่านทุกๆเส้นเชื่อมแต่ไม่ผ่านเส้นเชื่อมใดเส้นเชื่อมหนึ่งมากกว่าหนึ่งครั้ง&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;เลออนฮาร์ด ออยเลอร์ (Leonhard Euler) ชาวสวิตเซอร์แลนด์ที่ช่วงนั้นทำงานอยู่ที่เซนต์ ปีเตอร์สเบอร์ก สังเกตว่าปัญหาสะพานทั้งเจ็ดของเคอนิกสแบร์กจะมีคำตอบก็ต่อเมื่อไม่มีโหนดที่มีเส้นออกจากโหนดเป็นจำนวนคี่ หรือถ้ามีก็มีแค่สองโหนด เพราะการผ่านโหนดใดโหนดหนึ่งโดยไม่เดินซ้ำเส้นทางเดิมจะต้องมีทางเข้าทางหนึ่งกับทางออกทางหนึ่ง แต่โหนดเริ่มต้นไม่ต้องมีทางเข้าและโหนดสุดท้ายไม่ต้องมีทางออก คำตอบของออยเลอร์ลึกซึ้งที่ว่ามันไม่ใช่คำตอบของปัญหาสะพานทั้งเจ็ดของเคอนิกสแบร์กปัญหาเดียวแต่เป็นคำตอบของการเดินโดยไม่ซ้ำเส้นทางเดิมบนทุกๆเน็ตเวิร์ค และมันยังบอกขั้นตอนการหาคำตอบหรือ&lt;strong&gt;อัลกอริธึม&lt;/strong&gt; (algorithm) ที่มีประสิทธิภาพสำหรับทุกๆเน็ตเวิร์คโดยการนับจำนวนเส้นเชื่อมที่ออกจากโหนดแต่ละโหนดเท่านั้น&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ทว่าจนถึงทุกวันนี้ยังไม่มีใครรู้อัลกอริธึมเร็วๆสำหรับเกมไอโคเซียนที่ใช้ได้กับทุกๆเน็ตเวิร์ค ซึ่งน่าคิดเพราะเกมไอโคเซียนต่างกับปัญหาสะพานทั้งเจ็ดของเคอนิกสแบร์กเพียงแค่เปลี่ยนเส้นเชื่อมเป็นโหนดเท่านั้นเอง อัลกอริธึมที่ใช้ได้กับทั้งสองปัญหาก็คือลองเดินมันโง่ๆทุกเส้นทางบนเน็ตเวิร์คแล้วดูว่ามีเส้นทางที่เป็นคำตอบไหม แต่วิธีนี้อาจจะต้องใช้เวลาเป็นทวีคูณ (exponential) ของขนาดของเน็ตเวิร์ค จำนวนที่เป็นทวีคูณนี่ใหญ่ขนาดกันนะ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ในนิทานเรื่องหนึ่ง พระราชาเรียกผู้ที่คิดเกมหมากรุกได้เป็นคนแรกมาเข้าเฝ้าหวังจะให้รางวัลตอบแทนอย่างยิ่งใหญ่สมกับผลงานของเขา คนผู้นั้นก็ขอรางวัลเป็นข้าวสารหนึ่งเม็ดในช่องแรกของกระดานหมากรุก สองเม็ดในช่องที่สอง สี่เม็ดในช่องที่สาม… เพิ่มขึ้นที่ละสองเท่าตัวๆจนเต็ม 64 ช่องของกระดานหมากรุก พระราชาก็รับปากถึงแม้ในใจจะคิดว่าข้าวสารแค่นี้จะมีค่าสักเท่าไรเชียว จนกระทั่งคนรับใช้กะปริมาณข้าวสารที่ต้องให้&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1,000,000 เม็ดในช่องที่ 20&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1,000,000,000,000 เม็ดในช่องที่ 40&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;18,000,000,000,000,000,000 เม็ดในช่องสุดท้ายซึ่งถ้าตีเป็นน้ำหนักก็จะได้ประมาณ 460,000,000 ตัน!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/posts/08-2017/rice-on-chessboard.jpeg&quot; style=&quot;width: 750px;&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;บางเวอร์ชันของเรื่องเล่านี้จบลงที่พระราชาสั่งประหารคนผู้นั้นเมื่อรู้ตัวว่าโดนหลอกเข้าให้แล้ว บทเรียนหนึ่งของเรื่องนี้ก็คืออย่าไปกวนตีนคนที่มีอำนาจมากนัก แต่อีกบทเรียนที่สำคัญกว่าก็คือจำนวนที่โตแบบทวีคูณนั้นอาจจะโตเกินจินตนาการของเราได้ ถึงปัญหาจะไม่ใหญ่มาก แต่ถ้ามีแต่อัลกอริธึมที่ต้องใช้เวลาเป็นทวีคูณ ถึงจะใช้ซูเปอร์คอมพิวเตอร์ที่ทำการคำนวณได้กว่า 10 ยกกำลัง 15 ขึ้นตอนในหนึ่งวินาทีก็ยังอาจต้องใช้เวลาเกินอายุปัจจุบันของเอกภพ (13.7 พันล้านปี) ในขณะที่ดวงอาทิตย์อยู่ได้อีกแค่ประมาณห้าพันล้านปี อัลกอริธึมที่ช้าจึงไม่ใช่แค่ไม่ทันใจ แต่อาจจะไม่ทันโลกแตกด้วยซ้ำ! ปัญหาที่ต้องใช้เวลาเป็นทวีคูณในการแก้ถือเป็นปัญหาที่&lt;strong&gt;ยาก&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;บตรเครดต-เสยงดนตร-และคอมพวเตอรควอนตม&quot;&gt;บัตรเครดิต, เสียงดนตรี, และคอมพิวเตอร์ควอนตัม&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ไอเดียของคอมพิวเตอร์ที่อาศัยพฤติกรรมเชิงควอนตัมของสสารในการคำนวณมีมาตั้งแต่ปี 1980 แล้วแต่ในตอนนั้นยังไม่ชัดเจนว่าคอมพิวเตอร์ควอนตัมจะแก้ปัญหายากๆได้เร็วกว่าคอมพิวเตอร์ธรรมดาขนาดไหน จุดเปลี่ยนที่ทำให้คนหันมาสนใจคอมพิวเตอร์ควอนตัมในวงกว้างมาจากวงการที่แทบจะไม่เกี่ยวข้องกับฟิสิกส์เลย: วงการรหัสลับ&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;การส่งข้อความลับจะต้องมีกุญแจเข้ารหัส (encrypt) และกุญแจถอดรหัส (decrypt) รหัสลับก่อนสงครามโลกครั้งที่สองมักใช้กุญแจเดียวกันทั้งในการเข้าและถอดรหัส จึงถูกเรียกว่ากุญแจแบบสมมาตร (symmetric key) รหัสแบบนี้สามารถให้ความปลอดภัยอย่างสมบูรณ์แบบได้ในทางทฤษฎีเช่น one-time pad ที่มีกุญแจเป็นข้อความสุ่มมั่วๆเอามาใช้แปลงข้อความจริง ถ้ารู้ข้อความสุ่มนั้นก็จะกู้ข้อความจริงกลับมาได้ แต่กุญแจต้องใช้แล้วทิ้ง ห้ามใช้ซ้ำกัน ตามชื่อว่า one-time (การที่โปรเจ็กต์ VENONA ของ NSA สหรัฐอเมริกาจับตัวสายลับโซเวียตในช่วงสงครามโลกครั้งที่สองได้ก็เชื่อกันว่ามาจากการใช้กุญแจซ้ำของโซเวียตที่มีเหตุจากการเร่งการผลิตกุญแจลับเพราะการบุกของเยอรมัน) ยิ่งข้อความลับยาวกุญแจก็ยิ่งต้องใหญ่ นอกจากนี้การที่ทั้งผู้ส่งและผู้รับจะต้องมีกุญแจเดียวกันก็แปลว่าจะต้องมีการส่งกุญแจกันไปมา ถ้าถูกดักตีหัวขโมยกุญแจก็เสร็จ&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ในปัจจุบันรหัสลับส่วนใหญ่ใช้กุญแจคนละดอกในการเข้าและถอดรหัส โดยกุญแจเข้ารหัสเป็นกุญแจสาธารณะ (public key) ที่ใครๆก็รู้ได้ ระบบแบบนี้ไม่มีทางปลอดภัยอย่างสมบูรณ์แบบเพราะข้อมูลของกุญแจถอดรหัสก็อยู่ในกุญแจเข้ารหัส (ทั้งสองกุญแจมีความสัมพันธ์กันเพราะกุญแจถอดรหัสต้องแก้สิ่งที่กุญแจเข้ารหัสทำ) การค้นพบครั้งสำคัญในวงการรหัสลับคือการใช้ปัญหาการแยกตัวประกอบที่เชื่อว่าไม่มีอัลกอริธึมใดๆในปัจจุบันแก้ได้เร็วพอมาป้องกันการกู้กุญแจถอดรหัสจากกุญแจเข้ารหัส การเข้ารหัสนี้เรียกว่าการเข้ารหัสแบบ RSA &lt;a href=&quot;#fn1&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot; id=&quot;fnref1&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; และเป็นระบบการเข้ารหัสที่ใช้กันแพร่หลายในการเข้าเวบอย่างปลอดภัย (https), การป้องกันพาสเวิร์ด, หรือบัตรเครดิต ทุกครั้งที่เราซื้อของออนไลน์ ความปลอดภัยของเราขึ้นอยู่กับ RSA&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ถ้าดูนาฬิกาเป็นก็จะเข้าใจไอเดียของ RSA ได้ สังเกตว่าในการบวก-ลบเวลา เราจะไม่พูดว่า “10 ชั่วโมงหลัง 20 นาฬิกาคือ 30 นาฬิกา” แต่เราจะเริ่มนับส่วนที่เกิน 24 ใหม่ นอกจากบวก-ลบแล้วการคูณหรือการยกกำลังในระบบเลขคณิตแบบนี้ก็เป็นสิ่งที่ทำได้เพราะการคูณคือการบวกซ้ำๆกันและการยกกำลังคือการคูณซ้ำๆกัน ซึ่งคนส่วนใหญ่คงจะไม่เคยทำ แต่ถ้าลองทำดูจะพบสิ่งหนึ่งที่น่าสนใจคือการคูณเลขด้วยตัวมันเองซ้ำๆจะทำให้ย้อนกลับมายังเลขตั้งต้นได้ ตารางด้านล่างเป็นผลคูณ 2 ด้วยตัวมันเองถ้ามี 15 ชั่วโมงในหนึ่งวัน&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- https://stackoverflow.com/questions/24127507/is-it-possible-to-center-tables-in-a-markdown-file --&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;header&quot;&gt;
&lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;กำลัง&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;1&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;2&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;3&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;4&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;5&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;6&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;7&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;odd&quot;&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;ค่าของ 2 ยกกำลัง&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;การเข้ารหัสแบบ RSA แปลงข้อความให้เป็นจำนวนเต็มก่อน เรียกจำนวนนี้ว่า m (message) กุญแจสาธารณะคือจำนวนของ“ชั่วโมง” N และตัวเลข x ที่ทำให้ผู้เข้ารหัสสามารถคำนวณ m ยกกำลัง x ในเลขคณิตแบบนาฬิกาได้ เมื่อถึงมือผู้รับรหัส มีกุญแจลับ y ที่บอกว่าจะต้องยกกำลังต่ออีกเท่าไรจึงจะได้ข้อความ m กลับมา การจะรู้ y ได้จะต้องแยกตัวประกอบของ N ซึ่งเป็นส่วนหนึ่งของกุญแจสาธารณะที่ใครๆก็มี แต่ปัญหาก็คือทุกๆอัลกอริธึมการแยกตัวประกอบที่มีในปัจจุบันต้องใช้เวลาเป็นทวีคูณ การจะถอดรหัส RSA ที่ N เป็นเลขหลายร้อยหลักอาจจะต้องใช้เวลาเป็นล้านปี&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;แต่ถ้ามีคอมพิวเตอร์ควอนตัม การแยกตัวประกอบเลขหลายร้อยหลักจะใช้เวลาเพียงไม่กี่วินาที! &lt;a href=&quot;#fn2&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot; id=&quot;fnref2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; สิ่งที่ต่างก็คือคอมพิวเตอร์ควอนตัมมีอัลกอริธึมควอนตัมที่สามารถหาทางลัดในการแก้บางปัญหาได้ การทำงานของอัลกอริธึมควอนตัมแยกตัวประกอบค่อนข้างซับซ้อนแต่หัวใจของมันมาจากการทำงานร่วมกันของการยกกำลังในเลขคณิตนาฬิกากับการแปลงฟูเรียร์ (Fourier transform) การแปลงฟูเรียร์เป็นการแตกคลื่นเป็นผลรวมของหลายๆคลื่นที่มีความถี่เฉพาะตัว ไม่ต่างกับการแยกเสียงดนตรีเป็นโน๊ตความถี่ต่างๆ ทำให้สามารถขับหรือลดเสียงของเครื่องดนตรีแต่ละชนิดแยกกันได้ หน้าที่ของการแปลงฟูเรียร์ในอัลกอริธึมควอนตัมคือการหาคาบ (ส่วนกลับของความถี่) ของการยกกำลังในเลขคณิตนาฬิกา เมื่อรู้คาบ — จำนวนครั้งที่ต้องคูณเพื่อให้ได้ค่าเดิมกลับมา — ก็จะทำให้แยกตัวประกอบและรู้ y ได้ จึงทำลายรหัสลับ RSA ได้&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;บางปัญหาที่ยากสำหรับคอมพิวเตอร์ธรรมดาเป็นปัญหาที่ง่ายสำหรับคอมพิวเตอร์ควอนตัม นี่เป็นการค้นพบของ ปีเตอร์ ชอร์ (Peter Shor) ชาวอเมริกันในปี 1994 ที่สั่นสะเทือนวงการการถอดรหัสลับและฟิสิกส์ ปัจจุบันยังไม่มีคอมพิวเตอร์ควอนตัมขนาดใหญ่พอที่จะทำแบบนี้ได้ อินส์บรุค (Innsbruck) จับมือกับ MIT เพิ่งจะตีพิมพ์การแยกตัวประกอบ 15 ออกเป็น 3x5 ได้สำเร็จด้วยคอมพิวเตอร์ควอนตัมจิ๋ว 5 อะตอมเมื่อปีที่แล้ว &lt;a href=&quot;#fn3&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot; id=&quot;fnref3&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; แต่ก็ไม่ต้องห่วงว่าถ้าทำสำเร็จโลกนี้จะไม่มีความลับอีกต่อไปเพราะนักวิทยาศาสตร์ได้เตรียมรหัสลับต้านทานอัลกอริธึมควอนตัมไว้เรียบร้อยแล้ว (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Post-quantum_cryptography&quot;&gt;post-quantum cryptography&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;เรขาคณตของอลกอรธมควอนตม&quot;&gt;เรขาคณิตของอัลกอริธึมควอนตัม&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ความเข้าใจผิดที่ได้ยินกันแพร่หลายมากที่สุดเกี่ยวกับคอมพิวเตอร์ควอนตัมคือคอมพิวเตอร์ควอนตัมเหมือนกับคอมพิวเตอร์ธรรมดาที่ประมวลผลแบบคู่ขนาน แก้ปัญหาโดยการเช็คคำตอบทุกคำตอบที่เป็นไปได้พร้อมๆกัน ซึ่งถ้าทำได้จริงก็จะมหัศจรรย์มาก ไม่ว่าปัญหาใดๆ อัลกอริธึมควอนตัมที่ลองทุกคำตอบก็จะแก้ได้ในหนึ่งขั้นตอนเท่านั้น แต่ความจริงไม่ง่ายแบบนั้น ซึ่งก็อาจจะเป็นเรื่องดีเพราะการเข้ารหัสลับที่ต้านทานอัลกอริธึมควอนตัมก็ต้องอาศัยปัญหาที่ยากสำหรับทั้งอัลกอริธึมธรรมดาและอัลกอริธึมควอนตัม ตัวอย่างที่ดีเยี่ยมในการแสดงให้เห็นการความแตกต่างของการทำงานของอัลกอริธึมธรรมดากับอัลกอริธึมควอนตัมจึงเป็นอัลกอริธึมควอนตัมในการเช็คคำตอบที่ลอฟ โกรเวอร์ (Lov Grover) ชาวอเมริกัน-อินเดีย คิดขึ้นมาในปี 1996 หลังจากชอร์ 2 ปี&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;การจะเข้าใจการทำงานของอัลกอริธึมนี้จะต้องรู้พื้นฐานของทฤษฎีควอนตัมเสียก่อนทฤษฎีควอนตัมรวมคณิตศาสตร์ของความน่าจะเป็นกับเรขาคณิต แต่เป็นเรขาคณิตที่มีแต่ทิศทาง ไม่มีขนาด (สำหรับคนที่รู้จักเวกเตอร์ จึงไม่ใช่เรขาคณิตของเวกเตอร์เสียทีเดียวเพราะเวกเตอร์มีทั้งขนาดและทิศทาง) ในเรขาคณิตแบบนี้ เหนือกับใต้ถือว่าเป็นทิศเดียวกันเพราะการเดินไปทางเหนือก็คือการเดินไปทางใต้ด้วยระยะทางติดลบ พูดอีกอย่างก็คือมุม 180 องศากลายเป็น 0 องศา (แทนที่ 360 องศาจะเป็น 0 องศา) แต่ความใกล้กันของสองทิศทางก็ยังวัดได้ด้วยมุมที่ไม่เกิน 90 องศา สิ่งที่สำคัญคือยังมีทิศทางที่ตั้งฉากกัน (ทำมุม 90 องศา) นิยามของมิติจึงเหมือนกับในเรขาคณิตปกติ คือจำนวนที่มากที่สุดของทิศทางที่ตั้งฉากกัน เหมือนที่ 3 มิติมีความกว้าง ความยาว และความสูง &lt;a href=&quot;#fn4&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot; id=&quot;fnref4&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ระบบฟิสิกส์ไม่ว่าจะเป็นอะตอม ไอออน ช่องว่างในเพชร หรือวงจรไฟฟ้ายิ่งยวด ที่จะได้เจอในบทถัดๆไปของหนังสือเล่มนี้จะมีสถานะควอนตัม (quantum state) ของมันเองถ้าได้รับการป้องกันอย่างดีพอจากสิ่งรบกวนภายนอกไม่ว่าจะเป็นสนามแม่เหล็กไฟฟ้าหรือความร้อน ซึ่งตามทฤษฎีควอนตัมแล้ว ทิศทางเป็นตัวแทนเชิงคณิตศาสตร์ของสถานะควอนตัม ทิศทางนี้ไม่ใช่ทิศทางจริงๆในทางภูมิศาสตร์ แต่เป็นทิศทางในจำนวนมิติที่ถูกกำหนดโดยฟิสิกส์ของระบบนั้นๆ เช่นสถานะควอนตัมของสปินของอิเล็กตรอนถูกแทนด้วยทิศทางในสองมิติ&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;การวัดในทฤษฎีควอนตัมคือการถามระบบฟิสิกส์ว่าสถานะควอนตัมของเธอชี้ไปทางนี้หรือเปล่า? ถ้าทิศที่ถามขนานกับทิศที่มันชี้พอดีก็จะได้คำตอบว่า “ใช่” เสมอ ถ้าทิศที่ถามตั้งฉากกับทิศที่ชี้ก็จะได้คำตอบว่า “ใม่” เสมอ แต่จะเกิดอะไรขึ้นถ้าทิศที่ถามไม่ขนานหรือตั้งฉากเสียทีเดียวล่ะ? ทฤษฎีควอนตัมกำหนดว่าความน่าจะเป็นที่จะได้คำตอบ “ใช่” มีค่าเป็นกำลังสองของโคไซน์ของมุมระหว่างสองทิศนั้น&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- https://stackoverflow.com/questions/24127507/is-it-possible-to-center-tables-in-a-markdown-file --&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;header&quot;&gt;
&lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;องศา&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;0&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;30&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;45&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;60&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;90&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;120&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;135&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;150&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;180&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;odd&quot;&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;โคไซน์กำลังสอง&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;3/4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;1/2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;1/4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;1/4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;1/2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;3/4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;สมมติว่าปัญหาหนึ่งมีคำตอบที่เป็นไปได้ 4 คำตอบ ปกติแล้วจะต้องเช็คคำตอบทีละคำตอบ จึงเป็นไปได้ว่าจะต้องเช็คถึง 4 ครั้งกว่าจะได้คำตอบที่ถูกต้อง สำหรับคอมพิวเตอร์ควอนตัม 4 คำตอบนี้แทนด้วย 4 ทิศทางที่ตั้งฉากกัน (จึงมี 4 มิติ) การเช็คคำตอบด้วยการวัดก็ไม่ช่วยอะไรเช่นกัน แต่คอมพิวเตอร์ควอนตัมสามารถเช็คคำตอบโดยปราศจากการวัดได้โดยการเก็บคำตอบ “ใช่” หรือ “ไม่ใช่” ไว้กับตัวมันเอง ซึ่งถ้าเราไม่ไปวัดก็จะไม่รู้ ดูเป็นความสามารถที่ไร้ประโยชน์สิ้นดี แต่ทริคของอัลกอริธึมควอนตัมคือการแปลงการเช็คคำตอบแบบหลังไปเป็นการพลิกสถานะควอนตัมที่ขนานกับทิศของคำตอบ ถ้าคำตอบอยู่ในทิศเหนือ-ใต้ (อย่าลืมว่าเป็นทิศเดียวกันในเรขาคณิตแบบควอนตัม) แล้วสถานะควอนตัมชี้ไปทางเหนือ การเช็คคำตอบก็จะพลิกมันมาทางทิศใต้ สถานะควอนตัมที่ชี้ไปทางใต้ก็จะถูกพลิกไปยังทิศเหนือ และปล่อยทิศทางที่ตั้งฉากกับคำตอบไว้คงเดิม ทริคนี้จึงไม่มีผลต่อความน่าจะเป็นของผลการวัดแต่อย่างใด แต่มันทำให้อัลกอริธึมควอนตัมหาหนึ่งในสี่คำตอบที่ถูกต้องเจอจากการเช็ค (พลิก) เพียงหนึ่งครั้งเท่านั้น! เริ่มต้นด้วยทิศที่มีโอกาสได้คำตอบทุกคำตอบเท่าๆกันหมดคือ 1/4 ทิศนี้ทำมุม 60 องศากับคำตอบ s (solution) เพราะว่าโคไซน์กำลังสองของ 60 องศาเท่ากับ 1/4&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/posts/08-2017/grover2a.png&quot; style=&quot;width: 300px;&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;จากนั้นก็เช็คคำตอบเพื่อพลิกมัน&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/posts/08-2017/grover2b.png&quot; style=&quot;width: 650px;&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;แล้วก็พลิกอีกครั้งผ่านทิศตั้งต้นก็จะได้คำตอบที่ถูกต้องด้วยความน่าจะเป็น 100%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/posts/08-2017/grover2c.png&quot; style=&quot;width: 650px;&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;เมื่อคำตอบที่เป็นไปได้มีจำนวนเยอะขึ้น ทิศทางตั้งต้นก็จะอยู่ห่างจากทิศของคำตอบมากขึ้น การพลิกสองสเต็ป (จากการเช็คคำตอบ ตามด้วยการพลิกผ่านทิศตั้งต้น) แต่ละครั้งจะทำให้ขยับเข้าใกล้คำตอบมากขึ้นเรื่อยๆ หากทำการคำนวณก็จะประมาณได้ว่าจำนวนครั้งที่อัลกอริธึมนี้ต้องเช็คคำตอบคือรากที่สองของจำนวนคำตอบที่เป็นไปได้ &lt;a href=&quot;#fn5&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot; id=&quot;fnref5&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; ถ้าคอมพิวเตอร์ธรรมดาต้องเช็คคำตอบหนึ่งล้านครั้ง คอมพิวเตอร์ควอนตัมก็จำเป็นต้องเช็คเพียงแค่หนึ่งพันครั้ง ไม่ได้เร็วขึ้นแบบทวีคูณเหมือนอัลกอริธึมแยกตัวประกอบของชอร์แต่ก็ช่วยได้เยอะ&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ในมุมมองหนึ่ง สิ่งที่อัลกอริธึมควอนตัมทำจึงเป็นเพียงการขยับลูกศรไปมา ซึ่งพูดเหมือนง่ายแต่เป็นความท้าทายมาก ถ้าอยากรู้ว่าการควบคุมสถานะควอนตัมนั้นทำกันในแลบได้อย่างไรก็สามารถอ่านบทความที่เขียนและเรียบเรียงโดยนักศึกษาและนักวิทยาศาสตร์ไทยท่านอื่นๆ ได้ใน &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ebooks.in.th/ebook/45594/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;รูป รส กลิ่น เสียง สัมผัส ไอทีควอนตัม (๓): “คอมพิวเตอร์เชิงควอนตัม”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; ครับ&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;อางอง&quot;&gt;อ้างอิง&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cristopher Moore และ Stephan Mertens, “Quantum Computation” ใน &lt;em&gt;The Nature of Computation&lt;/em&gt;, Oxford University Press (2011).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Scott Aaronson, “Crypto” ใน &lt;em&gt;Quantum Computing Since Democritus&lt;/em&gt;, Cambridge University Press (2013).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;section class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn1&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;มาจากตัวอักษรแรกของชื่อผู้ค้นพบ Ron Rivest, Adi Shamir, และ Leonard Adleman&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn2&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;ถ้าสมมติว่าคอมพิวเตอร์ควอนตัมมีความเร็ว CPU พอๆกับของคอมพิวเตอร์ปัจจุบัน&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref2&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn3&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thomas Monz et al., “&lt;a href=&quot;http://science.sciencemag.org/content/351/6277/1068&quot;&gt;Realization of a scalable Shor algorithm&lt;/a&gt;” &lt;em&gt;Science&lt;/em&gt; 351 1068 (2016).&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref3&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn4&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;สำหรับผู้รู้ทฤษฎีควอนตัม ที่พูดไปไม่ใช่ความจริงทั้งหมดเพราะมุมนี้สามารถเป็นจำนวนเชิงซ้อนได้! แต่ทุกมุมในบทความนี้เป็นจำนวนจริง&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref4&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn5&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;จริงๆคือ &lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\(\pi/4\)&lt;/span&gt; คูณรากที่สองของจำนวนคำตอบที่เป็นไปได้&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref5&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>ควอนตัมฟิสิกส์สำหรับทารก</title>
   <link href="/quantum-for-babies.html"/>
   <updated>2016-12-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>h/quantum-for-babies</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;อาจจะเคยเห็นหนังสือ &lt;em&gt;Quantum Physics for Babies&lt;/em&gt; ที่ Mark Zuckerberg อ่านให้ลูกฟัง&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/posts/zuckerberg.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;หรือที่ “Antman” Paul Rudd ใช้เป็นที่พึ่งเพื่อหาวิธีเอาชนะ Stephen Hawking ในเกมหมากรุกควอนตัม&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Hi0BzqV_b44?t=5m4s&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Quantum Physics for Babies&lt;/em&gt; เป็นหนังสือที่ &lt;a href=&quot;https://csferrie.com/&quot;&gt;Chris Ferrie&lt;/a&gt; เขียนขึ้นมาให้ลูกของเขาเองระหว่างที่ทำงานเป็นโพสต์ด็อก(นักวิจัยหลังปริญญาเอก)ที่ University of New Mexico และเรียนรู้วิธี&lt;a href=&quot;https://csferrie.com/2016/11/19/quantum-physics-for-babies/&quot;&gt;ตีพิมพ์ด้วยตนเอง&lt;/a&gt; (เพราะจะได้เล่มตัวอย่างฟรี ถูกกว่าทำเล่มเอง) แล้วดันฮิตติดชาร์ทขึ้นมา คนขอเอาไปแปลเป็นภาษาจีน ภาษาเวียตนาม คราวนี้มีคนไทยคนหนึ่งทำงานร่วมกับเขาที่นิวเม็กซิโก &lt;em&gt;ควอนตัมฟิสิกส์สำหรับทารก&lt;/em&gt;ฉบับภาษาไทยจึงถือกำเนิดขึ้น&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;imgur-embed-pub&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot; data-id=&quot;a/D7MlQ&quot;&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;//imgur.com/D7MlQ&quot;&gt;Quantum Physics for Babies (THAI)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;script async src=&quot;//s.imgur.com/min/embed.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;คริสมอบสิทธิ์เกี่ยวกับ&lt;em&gt;ควอนตัมฟิสิกส์สำหรับทารก&lt;/em&gt;ฉบับภาษาไทยทั้งหมดให้กับผม (ผู้แปล) จะเอาไปให้สำนักพิมพ์ก็ได้ ถ้าหาสำนักพิมพ์ไม่ได้จะเอาไปแจกฟรีก็ได้ หลังจากรอคำตอบจากคนรู้จักที่ติดต่อให้ช่วยหาสำนักพิมพ์มาพักใหญ่ๆ ผมก็คิดว่าถึงเวลาเอามาแจกฟรีเป็นของขวัญปีใหม่ได้แล้ว สามารถดาวน์โหลดได้เลยที่&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Ninnat/quantum_physics_for_babies_THAI/releases&quot;&gt;ลิงค์นี้&lt;/a&gt; จะเอาไปปรินต์, ดัดแปลง, แชร์ไฟล์นี้หรือไฟล์ที่ได้รับการดัดแปลงให้ลูกเล็กเด็กแดงก็ได้เลยตามสบาย แต่ไม่อนุญาตให้นำไปใช้ทางการค้าและต้องให้เครดิตกับคริสและผม (นินนาท แดงเนียม) เสมอ&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;สวัสดีปีใหม่ครับ&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>First Post</title>
   <link href="/first-post.html"/>
   <updated>2016-07-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>h/first-post</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;First post on my Jekyll-powered blog!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve been blogging on &lt;a href=&quot;https://ninnatdangniam.wordpress.com/&quot;&gt;Wordpress&lt;/a&gt; for a long time (in Thai) but despite how easy it is to setup the blog, there isn’t much I can do without paying. Now you can follow &lt;a href=&quot;https://ninnat.github.io/README.html&quot;&gt;what I did&lt;/a&gt; and get your own blog hosted on a free (public) Git repository.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finding a blog that functions without a hassle is even harder if you are a math blogger, but that is not a problem here. Equations are written in &lt;a href=&quot;http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/&quot;&gt;Markdown&lt;/a&gt; and displayed using &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mathjax.org/&quot;&gt;MathJax&lt;/a&gt;. Math in a paragraph (in-line math) is delimited by &lt;code&gt;$...$&lt;/code&gt;, while displaying math in its own paragraph uses &lt;code&gt;$$...$$&lt;/code&gt;. Use &lt;code&gt;\begin{aligned}...\end{aligned}&lt;/code&gt; for aligned equations and &lt;code&gt;\begin{aligned}...\end{aligned}&lt;/code&gt; for numbered aligned equations. (Both delimiters have to be placed inside &lt;code&gt;$$...$$&lt;/code&gt;.) A quick guide on MathJax syntax can be found &lt;a href=&quot;http://meta.math.stackexchange.com/questions/5020/mathjax-basic-tutorial-and-quick-reference&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s test this by writing the Maxwell’s equations in cgs units:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;math&quot;&gt;\[
\begin{align}
\nabla \cdot \mathbf{E} &amp;amp;= 4\pi \rho , \\
\nabla \times \mathbf{E} &amp;amp;= -\frac{1}{c} \frac{\partial \mathbf{B}}{\partial t} , \\
\nabla \cdot \mathbf{B} &amp;amp;= 0, \\
\nabla \times \mathbf{B} &amp;amp;= \frac{4\pi}{c} \mathbf{J} + \frac{1}{c} \frac{\partial \mathbf{E}}{\partial t}.
\end{align}
\]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another indispensable feature that I’ve always longed for is the popup footnote. Digital footnotes today are often still implemented as if they are in print media. You follow the link to the bottom of the post and then have to find a way back to where you were in the main text, thus breaking the flow of reading. (And maybe it’s just me but it’s tempting to take a peek at footnotes even when I know they aren’t necessary to the main text.) A much better way to implement a digital footnote is using, for example, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bigfootjs.com/&quot;&gt;Bigfoot&lt;/a&gt; like this.&lt;a href=&quot;#fn1&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot; id=&quot;fnref1&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; All you have to do is pasting the css into &lt;code&gt;/assets/css/style.css&lt;/code&gt;, putting the javascript file to, say, &lt;code&gt;/assets/js&lt;/code&gt; and calling it with&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;script type=&amp;quot;text/javascript&amp;quot; src=&amp;quot;/assets/js/bigfoot.js&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;script type=&amp;quot;text/javascript&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
    $.bigfoot({
        activateCallback: function($popover, $button) {
                if (MathJax &amp;amp;&amp;amp; !$button.data(&amp;#39;mathjax-processed&amp;#39;)) {
                        var content_wrapper = $popover.find(&amp;#39;.bigfoot-footnote__content&amp;#39;)[0];
                        MathJax.Hub.Queue([&amp;#39;Typeset&amp;#39;, MathJax.Hub, content_wrapper]);
                        MathJax.Hub.Queue(function () {
                                $button.attr(&amp;#39;data-bigfoot-footnote&amp;#39;, content_wrapper.innerHTML);
                                $button.data(&amp;#39;mathjax-processed&amp;#39;, true);
                        });
                }
        }
    });
&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;within &lt;code&gt;/_includes/javascript.html&lt;/code&gt;. For searchability, I also choose to show footnotes in the footer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;3 Jan 2017&lt;/em&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;https://esham.io/2014/07/mathjax-and-bigfoot&quot;&gt;Benjamin Esham&lt;/a&gt; provides a code to enable MathJax in the footnotes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn1&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Alan Jacobs, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2012/03/the-technology-of-a-better-footnote/254403/&quot;&gt;“The Technology of a Better Footnote,”&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;The Atlantic&lt;/em&gt;, March 2012.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 
</feed>
