<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 
 <title>Ninnat's Notes</title>
 <link href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href=""/>
 <updated>2017-05-02T01:37:48+00:00</updated>
 <id></id>
 <author>
   <name>Ninnat Dangniam</name>
   <email>truecrimson@gmail.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Adjoint functors</title>
   <link href="/2017/01/26/adjoint-functors.html"/>
   <updated>2017-01-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>h/2017/01/26/adjoint-functors</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Modified: &lt;em&gt;28 Jan 2017&lt;/em&gt;; Status: &lt;em&gt;completed&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lately I’ve been thinking about induced representations and the Frobenius reciprocity theorem which have a natural interpretation in terms of adjoint functor in category theory. This post is an introduction to the categorical point of view situated in the intersection of what I’m confortable with and what I need. (You can find better general introductions out there written by mathematicians such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://topologicalmusings.wordpress.com/category/math-topics/category-theory/category-theory-for-beginners/&quot;&gt;this 3-parter&lt;/a&gt; by Todd Trimble.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first contact with category theory was through the book &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Mathematical-Physics-Chicago-Lectures/dp/0226288625&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mathematical Physics&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by Robert Geroch. There, category theory is seen to provide organizing principles to view seemingly unrelated constructions across many areas of mathematical physics. Ditto for mathematics. To me, one of the most powerful lesson from category theory is that knowing the relations between an object with other objects is as good as knowing the object itself, as the object can be defined by these relations. Occasionally, there is a unique (up to a natural isomorphism which doesn’t entail making any arbitrary choice) object that has a “universal” property that can simulate the relations to all other objects of the same kind and so can be thought of as the “best” object of its kind. As a bonus, all of these can be represented by diagrams of objects and arrows. I will give some examples of these on the way but let us first define what categories are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;strong&gt;category&lt;/strong&gt; \(\mathcal{C}\) is a class of objects and morphisms between them. If \(X\) and \(Y\) are &lt;strong&gt;objects&lt;/strong&gt; in \(\mathcal{C}\), the class of &lt;strong&gt;morphisms&lt;/strong&gt; between \(X\) and \(Y\) is denoted by \(\text{Hom}(X,Y)\). They are also represented diagrammatically as arrows \(f:X \to Y\) for \(f \in \text{Hom}(X,Y)\). For \(\mathcal{C}\) to be a category, there must be a unit (identity) morphism and the compositions of morphisms must be associative. Here are some categories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Set&lt;/strong&gt; of all sets. Since there is no &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Russell%27s_paradox&quot;&gt;set of all sets&lt;/a&gt;, the word “class” in the definition of a category cannot be replaced by “set”. The morphisms are arbitrary maps between sets.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Grp&lt;/strong&gt; of all groups, &lt;strong&gt;Ring&lt;/strong&gt; of all rings, and &lt;strong&gt;Field&lt;/strong&gt;\(_p\) of all fields with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Category_of_rings#Category_of_fields&quot;&gt;characteristic&lt;/a&gt; \(p=0\) or a prime number with the respective homomorphisms as morphisms. (There is no homomorphism between fields of different characteristics.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Top&lt;/strong&gt; of topological spaces with continuous maps as morphisms. In particular, homeomorphisms are isomorphisms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Man&lt;/strong&gt;\(^{\infty}\) of smooth manifolds with infinitely differentiable maps as morphisms. In particular, diffeomorphisms are isomorphisms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vec&lt;/strong&gt;\(_k\) of vector spaces over a field \(k\) with linear maps as morphisms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
My favorite elementary example of uniquely defining an object by morphisms is the construction of a product and a coproduct. A &lt;strong&gt;product&lt;/strong&gt; of \(A\) and \(B\) is an object \(C\) together with a morphism from \(C\) to \(A\) and \(B\) such that, if \(D\) is another object also equipped with some morphisms to \(A\) and \(B\), then there is a unique morphism from \(D\) to \(C\) such that the following diagram “commutes”, meaning that every way to compose such morphisms to go from \(D\) to \(A\) or \(B\) gives the same result.
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/posts/product.png&quot; style=&quot;width: 200px;&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;!-- \begin{align*}
    \xymatrix{
      &amp; D \ar[dl]_{\alpha&#39;}\ar[d]^{\gamma}\ar[dr]^{\beta&#39;} &amp; \\
      A &amp; C\ar[l]^{\alpha}\ar[r]_{\beta} &amp; B
    }
\end{align*} --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We call this kind of diagrams commutative diagrams. The rational behind this definition is that \(C\) together with the mappings \(\alpha\) and \(\beta\) is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Universal_property&quot;&gt;best&lt;/a&gt; object that acts as a product of \(A\) and \(B\) since giving any morphism from any object \(D\) to \(A\) or \(B\) is equivalent to giving \(\alpha\) and \(\beta\) from \(C\), so we can just forget about \(D\) altogether and regard \(C\) as a universal simulator of such relations.&lt;/p&gt;
The same diagram with all arrows reversed defines a &lt;strong&gt;coproduct&lt;/strong&gt; \(C\).
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/posts/coproduct.png&quot; style=&quot;width: 200px;&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;!-- \begin{align*}
    \xymatrix{
      &amp; D &amp; \\
      A\ar[ur]^{\alpha&#39;}\ar[r]_{\alpha} &amp; C\ar[u]_{\gamma} &amp; B\ar[l]^{\beta}\ar[ul]_{\beta&#39;}
    }
\end{align*} --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These definitions generalize trivially to a product and a coproduct of more than two objects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;strong&gt;Set&lt;/strong&gt;, the product is the direct product \(A \times B\) and the coproduct is the direct sum \(A \cup B\). We will just verify the first statement to familiarize ourselves with the meaning of the diagrams. For the direct product \(C=A \times B\), a natural choice for the mappings \(\alpha\) and \(\beta\) is the projection \[ \begin{aligned}
\alpha(a,b) = a, &amp;amp;&amp;amp; \beta(a,b) = b.
\end{aligned} \] We have to show that, for any \(\alpha&amp;#39;\) and \(\beta&amp;#39;\) from a set \(D\), there is a morphism \(\gamma\) from \(D\) to \(C\) that makes the diagram commutes and uniquely so. Obviously, for \(d\in D\), this map is \[ \begin{aligned}
\gamma(d) = (\alpha&amp;#39;(d),\beta&amp;#39;(d)),
\end{aligned} \] If there is another map \(\gamma&amp;#39;\) from \(D\) to \(C\) that makes the diagram commutes, it must sends \(d\) to an element of \(A \times B\) that projects to \(\alpha&amp;#39;(d)\) on \(A\) and \(\beta&amp;#39;(d)\) on \(B\). But that element is none other than \((\alpha&amp;#39;(d),\beta&amp;#39;(d))\). Thus, the uniqueness is established. For the direct sum \(C = A \cup B\), a natural choice for the mappings \(\alpha\) and \(\beta\) is the embedding of \(A\) and \(B\) into the union. Then the proof proceeds in the same manner by making obvious choices and following the arrows around (“diagram chasing”).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can ask if the direct product and the direct sum of sets are the only product and coproduct objects in &lt;strong&gt;Set&lt;/strong&gt;. The nice answer is that they are. And this is not only true in &lt;strong&gt;Set&lt;/strong&gt; but also in a general category as well. We will not prove that here but it amounts to using the definition of a product or a coproduct and do some more diagram chasing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why going so far to define something that should reduce to the notion of a product in any category? Well, this construction guides us when it is not clear what the right structure of the product is. This is the case in the category &lt;strong&gt;Top&lt;/strong&gt; of all topological spaces, which &lt;a href=&quot;https://topologicalmusings.wordpress.com/2008/06/22/basic-category-theory-i/&quot;&gt;Todd Trimble&lt;/a&gt; gives as an example and to which I will not go into since it is new to me so I would just be regurgitating what Todd already said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;functors&quot;&gt;Functors&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suppose that \(\mathcal{C}\) and \(\mathcal{D}\) are two categories and \(X,Y \in \mathcal{C}\). A (covariant) &lt;strong&gt;functor&lt;/strong&gt; \(F\) is a map (of both objects and morphisms) \(F: \mathcal{C} \to \mathcal{D}\) such that \(\text{Hom}(X,Y) \to \text{Hom}(F(X) , F(Y))\) preserves identity morphisms and compositions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most trivial kinds of functors are ones that simply throw away information. The &lt;strong&gt;forgetful functor&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Grp&lt;/strong&gt; \(\to\) &lt;strong&gt;Set&lt;/strong&gt; sends a group to its underlying set; it completely forgets the group structure. There are also functors that are partially forgetful such as the functor from &lt;strong&gt;Grp&lt;/strong&gt; to &lt;strong&gt;Ab&lt;/strong&gt; the category of all abelian groups which set \(ab=ba\) for all elements \(a,b\) in a group.&lt;/p&gt;
More interesting is the &lt;strong&gt;free functor&lt;/strong&gt; \(F:\) &lt;strong&gt;Set&lt;/strong&gt; \(\to\) &lt;strong&gt;Grp&lt;/strong&gt; sending a set to the “&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Free_group&quot;&gt;free group&lt;/a&gt;”. For a set \(S\), \(F(S)\) is the set of all expressions (“words”) that can be composed from elements of \(S\): every power and inverse of each and every element and (noncommutative) products of them; it is the least constrained group that can be built from elements of \(S\) as generators. The categorical way to say this is that the free functor has the universal property that any map \(\sigma\) from \(S\) to some group \(G\) factors through the free group \(F(S)\) with a unique group homomorphism \(\varphi\).
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/posts/free-group.png&quot; style=&quot;width: 150px;&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;!-- \begin{align*}
    \xymatrix{
      S \ar[r]\ar[dr]_{\sigma} &amp; F(S) \ar[d]^{\varphi} \\
      &amp; G
    }
\end{align*} --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a given group, the forgetful functor sends it to a particular set, and for a given set, the free functor sends it to a particular group. So they are in some sense inverse functors to each other even though the categories &lt;strong&gt;Set&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Grp&lt;/strong&gt; are clearly not the same. This concept of a generalized inverse is formalized in the notion of an adjoint functor.&lt;/p&gt;
Functors \(F: \mathcal{C} \to \mathcal{D}\) and \(G: \mathcal{D} \to \mathcal{C}\) are &lt;strong&gt;adjoint functors&lt;/strong&gt; if for any \(X \in \mathcal{C}\) and \(Y \in \mathcal{D}\), there is an &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adjoint_functors#Hom-set_adjunction&quot;&gt;isomorphism&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/posts/adjoint.png&quot; style=&quot;width: 180px;&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\[ \begin{aligned}
\text{Hom}_{\mathcal{D}} (F(X),Y) \simeq \text{Hom}_{\mathcal{C}} (X,G(Y)).
\end{aligned} \] &lt;!-- \begin{align*}
    \xymatrix{
      F(X)\ar[r]^{\text{Hom}_{\mathcal{D}}(F(X),Y)} &amp; Y\ar[d] \\
      X\ar[u]\ar[r]_{\text{Hom}_{\mathcal{C}}(X,G(Y))} &amp; G(Y)
    }
\end{align*} --&gt; \(F\) is called a &lt;strong&gt;left adjoint&lt;/strong&gt; of \(G\) and \(G\) is called a &lt;strong&gt;right adjoint&lt;/strong&gt; of \(F\).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why should this be true in the case of the forgetful functor \(E\) and the free functor \(F\) between &lt;strong&gt;Set&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Grp&lt;/strong&gt;? A group homomorphism \(\varphi :F(S) \to G\) is completely determined if we know what it does to each element of \(S\). In other words, what \(\varphi\) really acts on is the underlying set of \(G\). That is, giving \(\varphi\) is equivalent to giving \(\psi : S \to E(G)\). \[ \begin{aligned}
\text{Hom}_{\textbf{Grp}} (F(S),G) \simeq \text{Hom}_{\textbf{Set}} (S,E(G))
\end{aligned} \] so that the free functor is a left adjoint of the forgetful functor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A deep understanding of adjoint functors seem to require knowing about representability of functors and Yoneda’s lemma, neither of which I can competently explain. But they all have analogs in linear algebra by pretending that an inner product \(\braket{v,u}\) is a morphism \(\text{Hom}(v,u)\) in a category with one object \(V\) (with linear maps between vector spaces as functors). &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn1&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot; id=&quot;fnref1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. A functor $F: $&lt;strong&gt;Set&lt;/strong&gt; is &lt;strong&gt;representable&lt;/strong&gt; by \(X \in \mathcal{C}\) if the functor can be concretely realized as the morphism Hom\(_{\mathcal{C}}(X,\cdot)\). The &lt;strong&gt;Yoneda’s lemma&lt;/strong&gt; guarantees that this \(X\) is unique. In this analogy, the representability of \(F\) combined with the Yoneda’s lemma has the same content as the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Riesz_representation_theorem&quot;&gt;Riesz representation theorem&lt;/a&gt; in linear algebra. It says that a continuous linear functional \(f:V \to k\), where \(k\) is now the analog of &lt;strong&gt;Set&lt;/strong&gt;, can be identified as a unique vector in \(v \in V\) itself via the inner product \[ \begin{aligned}
f (u) = \braket{v,u}.
\end{aligned} \] Now consider the linear functional \(v \mapsto \braket{L(v),u}\). By the representation theorem, there is \(w \in V\) that realizes this map as \(\braket{v,w}\). This is an image of the adjoint operator \(w = L^*(u)\). By a similar argument, if \(F\) and \(G\) are adjoint functors \[ \begin{aligned}
\text{Hom}_{\mathcal{D}} (F(X),Y) \simeq \text{Hom}_{\mathcal{C}} (X,G(Y)),
\end{aligned} \] and the classes of morphisms are sets (which they usually are), the functor \(Y \mapsto \text{Hom}_{\mathcal{C}} (X,G(Y))\) is represented by \(F(X)\) and the functor \(X \mapsto \text{Hom}_{\mathcal{D}} (F(X),Y)\) is represented by \(F(Y)\), so they are unique by the Yoneda’s lemma. A further analogy is that an adjoint functor may not exist, but if it exists, it is unique.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In representation theory, a restriction of a representation of a group \(G\) to a subgroup \(H\) is a functor whose left adjoint is the induction of a representation of \(H\) to a “free” representation of \(G\). There, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Induced_representation&quot;&gt;Frobenius reciprocity theorem&lt;/a&gt; is nothing but the property of adjoint functors. I will talk about how this can be used to deduce the well known fact that each irreducible representation of SO(3) appears only once in the decomposition of functions on a sphere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn1&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Page 102 of Etingof &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://math.mit.edu/~etingof/replect.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Introduction to Representation Theory&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>ควอนตัมฟิสิกส์สำหรับทารก</title>
   <link href="/2016/12/27/quantum-for-babies.html"/>
   <updated>2016-12-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>h/2016/12/27/quantum-for-babies</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;อาจจะเคยเห็นหนังสือ &lt;em&gt;Quantum Physics for Babies&lt;/em&gt; ที่ Mark Zuckerberg อ่านให้ลูกฟัง&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/posts/zuckerberg.jpg&quot;&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;หรือที่ “Antman” Paul Rudd ใช้เป็นที่พึ่งเพื่อหาวิธีเอาชนะ Stephen Hawking ในเกมหมากรุกควอนตัม&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Hi0BzqV_b44?t=5m4s&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Quantum Physics for Babies&lt;/em&gt; เป็นหนังสือที่ &lt;a href=&quot;https://csferrie.com/&quot;&gt;Chris Ferrie&lt;/a&gt; เขียนขึ้นมาให้ลูกของเขาเองระหว่างที่ทำงานเป็นโพสต์ด็อก(นักวิจัยหลังปริญญาเอก)ที่ University of New Mexico และเรียนรู้วิธี&lt;a href=&quot;https://csferrie.com/2016/11/19/quantum-physics-for-babies/&quot;&gt;ตีพิมพ์ด้วยตนเอง&lt;/a&gt; (เพราะจะได้เล่มตัวอย่างฟรี ถูกกว่าทำเล่มเอง) แล้วดันฮิตติดชาร์ทขึ้นมา คนขอเอาไปแปลเป็นภาษาจีน ภาษาเวียตนาม คราวนี้มีคนไทยคนหนึ่งทำงานร่วมกับเขาที่นิวเม็กซิโก &lt;em&gt;ควอนตัมฟิสิกส์สำหรับทารก&lt;/em&gt;ฉบับภาษาไทยจึงถือกำเนิดขึ้น&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;imgur-embed-pub&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot; data-id=&quot;a/D7MlQ&quot;&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;//imgur.com/D7MlQ&quot;&gt;Quantum Physics for Babies (THAI)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;script async src=&quot;//s.imgur.com/min/embed.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;คริสมอบสิทธิ์เกี่ยวกับ&lt;em&gt;ควอนตัมฟิสิกส์สำหรับทารก&lt;/em&gt;ฉบับภาษาไทยทั้งหมดให้กับผม (ผู้แปล) จะเอาไปให้สำนักพิมพ์ก็ได้ ถ้าหาสำนักพิมพ์ไม่ได้จะเอาไปแจกฟรีก็ได้ หลังจากรอคำตอบจากคนรู้จักที่ติดต่อให้ช่วยหาสำนักพิมพ์มาพักใหญ่ๆ ผมก็คิดว่าถึงเวลาเอามาแจกฟรีเป็นของขวัญปีใหม่ได้แล้ว สามารถดาวน์โหลดได้เลยที่&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Ninnat/quantum_physics_for_babies_THAI/releases&quot;&gt;ลิงค์นี้&lt;/a&gt; จะเอาไปปรินต์, ดัดแปลง, แชร์ไฟล์นี้หรือไฟล์ที่ได้รับการดัดแปลงให้ลูกเล็กเด็กแดงก็ได้เลยตามสบาย แต่ไม่อนุญาตให้นำไปใช้ทางการค้าและต้องให้เครดิตกับคริสและผม (นินนาท แดงเนียม) เสมอ&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;สวัสดีปีใหม่ครับ&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>First Post</title>
   <link href="/2016/07/20/first-post.html"/>
   <updated>2016-07-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>h/2016/07/20/first-post</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Modified: &lt;em&gt;3 Jan 2017&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First post on my Jekyll-powered blog!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve been blogging on &lt;a href=&quot;https://ninnatdangniam.wordpress.com/&quot;&gt;Wordpress&lt;/a&gt; for a long time (in Thai) but despite how easy it is to setup the blog, there isn’t much I can do without paying. Now you can follow &lt;a href=&quot;https://ninnat.github.io/README.html&quot;&gt;what I did&lt;/a&gt; and get your own blog hosted on a free (public) Git repository.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finding a blog that functions without a hassle is even harder if you are a math blogger, but that is not a problem here. Equations are written in &lt;a href=&quot;http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/&quot;&gt;Markdown&lt;/a&gt; and displayed using &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mathjax.org/&quot;&gt;MathJax&lt;/a&gt;. Math in a paragraph (in-line math) is delimited by &lt;code&gt;$...$&lt;/code&gt;, while displaying math in its own paragraph uses &lt;code&gt;$$...$$&lt;/code&gt;. Use &lt;code&gt;\begin{aligned}...\end{aligned}&lt;/code&gt; for aligned equations and &lt;code&gt;\begin{aligned}...\end{aligned}&lt;/code&gt; for numbered aligned equations. (Both delimiters have to be placed inside &lt;code&gt;$$...$$&lt;/code&gt;.) A quick guide on MathJax syntax can be found &lt;a href=&quot;http://meta.math.stackexchange.com/questions/5020/mathjax-basic-tutorial-and-quick-reference&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s test this by writing the Maxwell’s equations in cgs units:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\[
\begin{align}
\nabla \cdot \mathbf{E} &amp;amp;= 4\pi \rho , \\
\nabla \times \mathbf{E} &amp;amp;= -\frac{1}{c} \frac{\partial \mathbf{B}}{\partial t} , \\
\nabla \cdot \mathbf{B} &amp;amp;= 0, \\
\nabla \times \mathbf{B} &amp;amp;= \frac{4\pi}{c} \mathbf{J} + \frac{1}{c} \frac{\partial \mathbf{E}}{\partial t}.
\end{align}
\]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another indispensable feature that I’ve always longed for is the popup footnote. Digital footnotes today are often still implemented as if they are in print media. You follow the link to the bottom of the post and then have to find a way back to where you were in the main text, thus breaking the flow of reading. (And maybe it’s just me but it’s tempting to take a peek at footnotes even when I know they aren’t necessary to the main text.) A much better way to implement a digital footnote is using, for example, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bigfootjs.com/&quot;&gt;Bigfoot&lt;/a&gt; like this. &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn1&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot; id=&quot;fnref1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; All you have to do is pasting the css into &lt;code&gt;/assets/css/style.css&lt;/code&gt;, putting the javascript file to, say, &lt;code&gt;/assets/js&lt;/code&gt; and calling it with &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;script type=&amp;quot;text/javascript&amp;quot; src=&amp;quot;/assets/js/bigfoot.js&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt; &amp;lt;script type=&amp;quot;text/javascript&amp;quot;&amp;gt;     $.bigfoot({         activateCallback: function($popover, $button) {                 if (MathJax &amp;amp;&amp;amp; !$button.data(&#39;mathjax-processed&#39;)) {                         var content_wrapper = $popover.find(&#39;.bigfoot-footnote__content&#39;)[0];                         MathJax.Hub.Queue([&#39;Typeset&#39;, MathJax.Hub, content_wrapper]);                         MathJax.Hub.Queue(function () {                                 $button.attr(&#39;data-bigfoot-footnote&#39;, content_wrapper.innerHTML);                                 $button.data(&#39;mathjax-processed&#39;, true);                         });                 }         }     }); &amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; within &lt;code&gt;/_includes/javascript.html&lt;/code&gt;. This code, created by &lt;a href=&quot;https://esham.io/2014/07/mathjax-and-bigfoot&quot;&gt;Benjamin Esham&lt;/a&gt;, enables MathJax in the footnote. You also have the option to show or hide footnotes in the footer. I decide to show it for searchability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn1&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Alan Jacobs, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2012/03/the-technology-of-a-better-footnote/254403/&quot;&gt;“The Technology of a Better Footnote,”&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;The Atlantic&lt;/em&gt;, March 2012.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 
</feed>
